<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An order of houshold instruction by which euery master of a familie, may easily and in short space, make his whole houshold to vnderstand the principall and chiefe points of Christian religion, without the knowledge whereof, no man can be saued.</title>
            <author>Nichols, Josias, 1555?-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18539.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23190901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23190901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26366</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08202)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An order of houshold instruction by which euery master of a familie, may easily and in short space, make his whole houshold to vnderstand the principall and chiefe points of Christian religion, without the knowledge whereof, no man can be saued.</title>
                  <author>Nichols, Josias, 1555?-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[119] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the VVidowe Orwin, for Thomas Man, dwelling in Pater-noster row, at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iosias Nichols.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸ H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded and torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:1"/>
            <p>AN ORDER OF HOVSHOLD INSTRVCTION: By which euery maſter of a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>may eaſily and in ſhort ſpace, make</hi> his whole houſhold to vnderſtand the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and chiefe points of Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: without the knowledge whereof, no man can be ſaued.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. <hi>6.</hi> verſ. <hi>6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thine heart, &amp; thou ſhalt rehearſe them continually vnto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt in thine houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt knowne the holie Scriptures of a childe, which are able to make thee wiſe vnto ſaluation, thorough the faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONON <hi>Printed by the VVidowe Orwin, for</hi> Thomas Man, dwelling in Pater-noſter row, at the ſigne of the Talbot. 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE LORD ROBERT DEVOREVX, Earle of Eſſex and Ewe, Vicount Hereford, and Bourchier, Lord Ferrers and Chartly, Lord Bourchier, and Louaine, Knight of the noble Order of the Garter, Maſter of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Horſe, and one of her Maieſties moſt Honorable priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a matter of great waight, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie duety, Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, to conſider wiſely, and to iudge rightly of the workes of God, in the euent of thinges which happen vnto
<pb facs="tcp:26366:3"/>men. For as it is written in the Pſalmes:
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.17.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his waies, and holy in all his workes.</hi> And againe:
<note n="b" place="margin">107.43.</note> 
               <hi>VVho is wiſe that hee may obſerue theſe things? for they ſhall vnderstand the louing kindneſſe of the Lorde.</hi> And againe:
<note n="c" place="margin">92.6.</note> 
               <hi>An vnwiſe man knoweth it not, and a foole doth not vnderstand this.</hi> And ſeeing
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</note> all thinges are of him, and thorow him, &amp; for him, and
<note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.9.</note> in his owne might no man ſhall bee ſtrong: but
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 75.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.11.</note> God is Iudge, hee maketh low, he maketh high; and that the counſell of the Lorde ſhall ſtand for euer, &amp; the thoughtes of his hart,
<note place="margin">Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in all things is to be obſerued.</note> thoroughout all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: euery man ought carefully to regarde the prouidence of
<pb facs="tcp:26366:3"/>God, in the thinges befalling to himſelf and others, which I find very fruitfully obſerued by the holy ſeruaunts of GOD in the Scriptures. As Ioſeph, when he ſawe his Fathers houſe, in the time of the greate famine, to come into Egypt to buy foode, comforteth his brethren, who of enuie had ſolde him thither, with this obſeruation, ſaying:
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5.</note> 
               <hi>Bee not ſad, neither grieued with your ſelues, that ye ſold me hither: for God did ſende me before you, for your preſeruation.</hi> And Dauid comforteth himſelfe, and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the rage of his ſeruaunt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the curſing of Shimei, by this conſideration, ſaying,
<note n="h" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12</note> 
               <hi>Jt may bee that God will looke vpon
<pb facs="tcp:26366:4"/>mine affliction, &amp; do me good for his curſing this day.</hi> So Mordecai en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth Eſter, to make ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the king (though it were contrarie to lawe, and in hazard of her life) in the behalf of the Iewes, who were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die by wicked Haman: by ſuch a wiſe collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among other wordes, ſaying:
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>VVho knoweth whether thou art come to the kingdome for ſuch a time?</hi> In like ſorte, when I thinke vpon your honor, remembring what I haue heard of your noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that good Erle, in the time of his laſt ſicknes, &amp; of his godly care ouer his children: compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereunto how God hath preſerued you vnto this time,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:4"/>what ſpeciall fauour you haue attained before ſo gracious a Prince, in what an high &amp; waigh tie place you are ſet, &amp; in what yeares of your age theſe things are befallen you, together with the bleſſed giftes by which you are fitted thereunto: mine hart is touched with a comfortable hope, that the Lords grace wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king effectually in you, and his heauenly ſpirite directing you: you might be a worthie inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in faithfull and wiſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to her maieſty for the good of this common-wealth, &amp; the churches of Ieſus Chriſt among vs. For if
<note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.4.</note> Obadiah vnder wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ahab, could keepe from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel, and feede an hundreth
<pb facs="tcp:26366:5"/>Prophetes: and
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 38.8.9.</note> Ebedmelech could obtaine of that euill king Zedekiah, to deliuer Ieremie out of the dungeon, into which he was caſt by the Princes with the kings conſent: and
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.</note> Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah could apply the fauour he had with that heatheniſh King Artaſhaſht, to the building of the walles of Hieruſalem: who can tell? but that much more, ſuch a noble man of Chriſtian knowledge, aduanced by God into the fauour of ſo Chriſtian and religious a princeſſe, may likewiſe performe ſome ſeruice of great importance, to the Church of God and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</p>
            <p>And verily if God
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u.</hi> 18.4.</note> made all
<pb facs="tcp:26366:5"/>for himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Euery man ought to ſerue God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his place &amp; giftes.</note> and his elect
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe</hi> 1, 6.</note> for the glorie of his grace,
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.26.</note> aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the times, which were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before, and the bounds of mens habitation, that they ſhould ſeeke the Lord: and if he haue
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.14.</note> giuen euery man a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, whereof hee muſt render an account; then ought euerie man
<note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17.24</note> ſo to walke, as God hath diſtributed to euery man, as the Lorde hath called euery one, and therein to abide with God. Therfore
<note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> Saul, without reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of any ſpoyle, by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, muſt bee obedient to the voyce of the Lord, in the vtter deſtroying of Amalecke; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had annoynted him to be king, &amp; called him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.
<pb facs="tcp:26366:6"/>And Dauid,
<note n="l" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> though hee were a man after Gods heart: yet becauſe he forgate his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement by God, &amp; his great benefits, and by deflowring his neighbours wife, &amp;c. diſobeied God, and cauſed the enemies of God to blaſpheme: was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſharply &amp; puniſhed ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And thou O meeke
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 30.12</note> Moſes, what kept thee out of the lande of promiſe? And thou O wiſe
<note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 11.</note> Salomon, what made thy lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes troubleſome, and a breach in thy kingdome? And thou O good
<note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.</note> Iehoſhaphat, what brought thy life in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard? was it not, that God, who exalted you in honour,
<note place="margin">Who ſo honor not God are plagued.</note> was not ſanctified by your ſeruice? If
<pb facs="tcp:26366:6"/>God thus deale with his owne
<note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17.</note> houſe, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinners appeare?
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.19.</note> whoſe God is their bellie, who
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Haback.</hi> 1.16.</note> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the net of their own po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, and honour the
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.13.</note> God ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2.</note> know not the Lord, who giueth them all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to enioy?
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24.</note> God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them ouer to their owne luſts,
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.14.</note> they meete with darknes in the day time, and grope at noone day as in the night, ſome by
<note n="k" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23</note> their policie make an halter to hang themſelues, ſome in the
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 5.</note> middeſt of their iolitie, haue the ioynts of their loynes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and their knees ſmitten one againſt another, and ſome are
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 53.5. <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 28.1.</note> afeard where there is no feare,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:7"/>and flye when no man purſueth them. And
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.24.</note> as the flame of fire deuoureth the ſtubble, and as the chaffe is conſumed of the flame; ſo their roote ſhall bee rottennes, and their bud ſhall riſe vp as duſt, becauſe they haue caſt off the lawe of the Lord of hoſts, &amp;c. that it might ſtand as an vnchaungeable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the hie God, the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of heauen and earth; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the wicked &amp; the true ſeruants of God:
<note n="o" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. The feare of God rewarded</note> 
               <hi>Them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor me, I will honor, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed.</hi> So did the Lord aduance vertuous
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.</note> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, before all his brethren, he
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.21.</note> made houſes to the widowes, who feared God in Egypt, and
<pb facs="tcp:26366:7"/>deliuered
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 39.16.</note> Ebedmelech in the day of euill. Therefore, for the comfort of all them, that walke according to their gifts &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with God, it is written:
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.18.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the eye of the Lord is vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him, and vpon them that truſt in his mercie, to deliuer their ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in famine.</hi> For this cauſe (right Honorable) haue I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to dedicate this ſmall booke to your Honour, not onely becauſe I am perſwaded of your fauorable acceptation, but alſo that by mee being one among many, you might know what hope and expectation there is, among her Maieſties moſt faithfull ſubiects concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:26366:8"/>you: that your yong yeres being ſanctified, and (
<note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.14.</note> as S. Iohn ſaith) being ſtrong &amp; the word of God abiding in you, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouercome the wicked, you might amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt other graue and wiſe counſellors, bee a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labourer in all good cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and a proſperous furtherer of things concerning God, to the great ioy, peace and honor, of her moſt excellent maieſtie, and that by the mouthes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny her louing ſubiects, prayſes may redound to the glorie of God, and that you may glorie in his praiſe. And here I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie craue your Chriſtian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to giue mee leaue to tell you, what the Lorde ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:26366:8"/>vnto you. For me thinketh I heare him ſpeake vnto you, as he did vnto Ioſhuah and Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſhu.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Be thou ſtrong and of a moſt valiant courage, that thou mayst obſerue and doe according to al the law, which Moſes my ſeruant hath commanded thee: thou ſhalt not turne away from it, to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor to the left, that thou maiſt proſper whither ſoeuer thou goeſt. I will be with thee, J will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 17.1.</note> Feare not, J am thy buckler and thine excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reward. J am God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, walke before me and bee vpright.</hi> Now this little booke of houſhold inſtruction, I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto your Honors protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nothing comparable to
<pb facs="tcp:26366:9"/>the profound works ſet foorth by rare and ſingular men, but as a little candle to bee placed in the midſt of the houſe, to giue light to all them that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And as in the worke of the materiall Temple vnder Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note n="c" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.2.</note> hewers of ſtones had a neceſſary vſe: ſo this little book may bee ſome good helpe, to prepare the ſeueral members of the familie, for the ſkilfull buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that is, the
<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> faithful mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to be ioined as liuely ſtons in the ſpirituall temple of God. For as the Pſalmiſt doth teſtifie:
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130</note> 
               <hi>The entrance into Gods wordes ſheweth light, and giueth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing vnto the ſimple.</hi> And our Sauiour teacheth, that there is a
<pb facs="tcp:26366:9"/>ſecret working in his kingdom, like the growing of the
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſmall graine of muſtard-ſeed, and as a little leaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hid in three pecks of meale: So
<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.</note> God hath choſen fooliſh thinges of the world to confound the wiſe, &amp; God hath choſen weake thinges of the world to confound the mighty, &amp;c. And to whom ſhould I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the booke of teaching the familie? but euen to him, whoſe houſhold being well inſtructed, ordered, &amp; guided, may diuers waies doe good vnto many of all eſtates and degrees: yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to him, who knoweth verie well, how needfull a thing it is in regarde of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: which in troubleſome
<pb facs="tcp:26366:10"/>times doth find, that a Chriſtian Prince cannot be ſure of ſuch a peoples faithfulnes, in dayes of triall: whoſe bellies being fedde with the fatte of the earth, haue mindes vnſetled; and for lacke of the knowledge of Chriſt, and the feare of God, are apt to go after the ſway of time, and to bee led as beaſtes by the bellie, where moſt eaſe, gaine, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhall draw them. Therefore nothing doubting, but that your godly wiſedom, and good knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus, will graciouſly receiue any thing, that may be helpful to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion and godlines: I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this little booke vnto your Honour, with al humblenes and
<pb facs="tcp:26366:10"/>good will in the Lord; leauing the ſucceſſe vnto him, in whoſe handes are the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 31.15.</note> times of all things, and
<note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.</note> who onely giueth increaſe. Moſt meekely pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his diuine goodnes to make you honorable in this world, in all pietie and Chriſtian vertues, to the glory of his name, the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of your Prince and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and to the reioycing of all good chriſtians: &amp; in the world to come, to bee partaker of his glory: who ſhall be glorified in his Saintes, and made maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in all that beleeue. Amen. At Eaſtwell in Kent this 26. of Februarie. Anno 1596.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours alwaies to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi>
IOSIAS NICHOLS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:11"/>
            <head>To all gouernours of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <hi>grace and peace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Very well remember, my welbeloued country me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye that are gouernours of families, that he was a wiſe Preacher, that ſayde:
<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>12.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is no ende in making many bookes.</hi> And that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny very good and excellent Catechiſmes are publiſhed in our Engliſh tongue: being not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very profitable for Chriſtians, to exerciſe themſelues in: but alſo moſt notable tokens of the Chriſtian care and loue, of diuers learned and godly minded men, toward their neighbors and countrie. Yet haue I ſome good reaſons (as I thinke) to put foorth this little booke of mine as a mite, in compariſon of the greateſt gifts of other men, who by their excellent workes, haue greatly repleniſhed the Lords treaſurie. Firſt, becauſe that I finde that the Lord in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Church vſeth the diuers gifts of
<pb facs="tcp:26366:12"/>his ſeruants, to expreſſe his manifold wiſedom. And as vnto men of diuers complexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, he hath giuen choiſe of meate and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of apparell: ſo, many bookes to one end are ſet foorth in diuers faſhions and with a diuers gift, order and facilitie: that hee whome one booke ſauoureth not, might yet like the taſte of another. So it may bee, that I ſtriuing to enter into the loweſt place of the Church, which is the familie; and applying my ſelfe to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort, may happily finde a place to doe good vnto ſome, where books of greater excellencie, peraduenture are not entertained: and ioyning hands with my good brethren, who haue ſorted themſelues to the ſame ſtanding place, may by ioynt working with them, peraduenture further their ioy, as they doe mine. Secondly, becauſe I haue ſome experience in this order, that it may prepare them, which are hereby inſtructed, to haue their eyes open to other mens labours. And I am in great hope, that a diſcreet teacher ſhall finde by triall, that a childe of very tender yeres may be made able, through Gods bleſſing, with vnderstanding to giue a good reckoning of his faith, by the Scriptures. Moreouer, my purpoſe was not, curiouſly to ſet downe all points of doctrine, but especially thoſe, which doe moſt neerely teach theſe two:
<note n="a" place="margin">Act. <hi>20.21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Repentance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and faith in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And my deſire was that theſe might be made to appeare
<pb facs="tcp:26366:12"/>eaſie and familiar by the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But aboue all other this moued mee moſt, that I might haue occaſion to ſpeake ſome things to the gouernours of the families, which doe very greatly affect my minde. Which is not to proue it their duties, to catechiſe their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or to deſcribe the houſhold gouernment, &amp; diuers ſuch things which I know to be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently penned downe by others: but onely to lay before them, the great neceſſitie of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the great and honorable ſeruice, which a priuate man may doe, to God and his people, by this meanes. In doing whereof, I thought no better meane, then the ſetting foorth of an eaſie way, to doe the thing, to which I deſire earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perſwade them.</p>
            <p>The neceſſitie will be ſeene,
<note place="margin">Neceſſitie to teach houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes.</note> if they obſerue with me two things, the time preſent, and the time likely to enſue. In the firſt they ſhall finde, that although wee haue had the Gospell, by the mercie and long ſuffering of God ſeuen and thirtie yeares, vnder the happie raigne of our moſt deare and gracious Soueraigne Ladie Queene Elizabeth, (who, I heartily pray our good God, may yet raigne many yeares ouer vs) there are to bee found ſo many that know not how they ſhall bee ſaued, or how they are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, why they are called Chriſtians, what is Chriſt in his perſon, and ſuch like (which
<note n="b" place="margin">Hebr. <hi>6.1.2.</hi> Pſalm. <hi>49.20.</hi>
               </note> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginner and yongling in Chriſt ought to be
<pb facs="tcp:26366:13"/>skilfull in;
<note place="margin">Lamentable ignorance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs.</note> and without the knowledge whereof a man is like a bruit beaſt) that I doe tremble to thinke, and am aſhamed to vtter, and dare not commit to writing my knowledge herein. I haue had conference in ſome pariſhes with <hi>400.</hi> ſome, <hi>1000.</hi> ſome leſſe, and haue made triall, and do make triall euery day, that I ſpeake to any man, whom I knowe not, that I am aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to thinke, that ſo many Chriſtians in name, and baptized, ſhould bee ſo ignorant and brutiſh, and ſo farre from being indeede, that which they delight to bee called. For I take it, that
<note n="c" place="margin">Galat. <hi>3.26.</hi>
               </note> faith maketh the being of a Chriſtian, and theſe
<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. <hi>10.14.</hi>
               </note> who haue no knowledge cannot haue faith, which will then appeare,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Theſſ <hi>1.8.</hi>
               </note> when Chriſt ſhall come in flaming fire, to render vengeance to them that do not know God. Therfore there is a great fault, whether it be in vs Miniſters, or in you the maſters of families, or in both, the Lord bee mercifull vnto vs, our danger is very great: for it is written,
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. <hi>1.23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As they regarded not to know God, ſo God deliuered them vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reprobate minde, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore it is a thing of neceſſitie, that ſuch as keepe houſes, ſhould traine vp their people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to their charge,
<note place="margin">Many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters teach not.</note> in the knowledge of the Goſpel. Againe, we that are Miniſters, for the moſt part, are very vntidie for theſe workes, which might preuent this miſchiefe.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Tim. <hi>4.10.</hi>
               </note> Some imbracing this preſent world, and ſome being
<note n="c" place="margin">Math. <hi>15.14.</hi>
               </note> blind leaders of
<pb facs="tcp:26366:13"/>the blinde. Therefore the maſters of families looking not vnto this matter, the caſe is become lamentable. The time likely to enſue may bee very much iudged by the preſent.
<note place="margin">Coldnes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that God hath warned vs, to make more reuerent regard of his Gospell, by windes and vnſeaſonable weather, by diuers ſickneſſes, by the plague and dearth &amp; feare of the ſword, not once nor twiſe within theſe fewe yeares: yet the great careleſnes and coldnes (that I ſay not contempt) of religion, may hereby appeare, that Atheiſme, dronkennes, and other very great ſinnes, are waxen bold and ſhameles, and he that feareth an oth, and taketh great paines to bee instructed in Chriſt Ieſus, ſuffereth no ſmall moleſtation. What may we then looke for? but as theſe former corrections, haue brought vs no one iot neerer to repentance, or loue of Gods word, ſo the Lord will yet ſtretch out his hand againſt vs. And what can we tell, that if other temporall plagues moue vs not, but that he will take away his word from an vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nation,
<note place="margin">We may ſeare the loſſe of the goſpell.</note> and giue it to another that will bring foorth better fruites? If we that be Ministers ouerſtip theſe things, how can they be repaired, but by the inſtruction of families. And many times when we take great paines, the backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the maſters doth pull downe all that wee build. Therefore it is of great neceſſitie, that the gouernours of houſholds ſhould ſtirre vp
<pb facs="tcp:26366:14"/>themſelues to this duetie.</p>
            <p>Now the honorable ſeruice, which a priuate man may do to God and his Church,
<note place="margin">Teaching the familie hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſeruice to God.</note> appeareth in this; that ſuch as traine their families in theſe good grounds, bring foorth an holy gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the Church, and a ciuill nation to the Common-wealth; which doth not a little ſhewe it ſelfe to Gods glorie, and the praiſe of the Goſpell, in our owne experience. Whereof the example of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his familie, <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his ſouldiers, <hi>Abraham</hi> and his three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and eighteene, brought vp in his houſe, are as ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonies. How are the names of many priuate men and women for their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the Church, commended by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and regiſtred to immortall fame and example of all profeſſors,
<note place="margin">Priuate men and women may greatly further the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Rom. 16.</hi> So that among many he acknowledgeth, that all the Churches of the Gentiles were to bee thankefull to one <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> his wife. And God doth ſo farre honour the houſe of
<note n="a" place="margin">Ierem. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rechab,</hi> that he poynteth it out, and ſetteth it foorth, to be an euerlaſting paterne, of the notable fruite of good gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of families. And as
<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. <hi>35.25.</hi>
               </note> women did worke diuers things for the tabernacle, in the daies of Moſes: and as the
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> King. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> temple was not built, but by men of all ſorts in the time of <hi>Salomon:</hi> and the
<note n="d" place="margin">Nehem. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> walles of Ieruſalem vnder the guiding of <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> So may priuate men very much further the building of the ſpirituall temple,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:14"/>which is the congregation of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſpring out of inſtructed families.</note> And as out of Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacobs houſe, ſprang forth the Churches of the Iewes: ſo the glorious congregations of the Gentiles, began in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: For if ſeruants well nurtured
<note n="e" place="margin">Tit. <hi>2.10.</hi>
               </note> may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne the doctrine of God our Sauiour in all thinges: and
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>3.1.</hi>
               </note> huſbands obeying not the worde, may without the word be wonne, by the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the wiues: how much more may the maſter of the familie doe vnto God and his Church honorable ſeruice? not only by ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his houſe by the word of faith; but alſo by hauing alwaies in a readines, very notable matter to further the building of Gods dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place. Which thing is auouched to thee by
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.5.</hi> and <hi>3.15.</hi> with Act. <hi>16.1.</hi>
               </note> young <hi>Timotheus,</hi> who being brought vp in the holy Scriptures from a childe, vnder his faithfull grandmother <hi>Lois,</hi> and his mother <hi>Eunice,</hi> when he was yet a very young man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a companion of the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in that great and waightie worke of planting Churches. And
<note n="h" place="margin">Act. <hi>18.24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apollos</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth the ſame, who being an eloquent man and mightie in the Scriptures, was yet more perfectly inſtructed in the way of God, by the houſe of a craftſman: by whom not onely they which beleeued thorow grace, were very much holpen; but alſo the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of Chriſt were mightily confuted by the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, I pray you to marke diligently,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:15"/>how that the diſorder of one priuate familie,
<note place="margin">One familie well or ill or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, may ſaue or deſtroy both Church &amp; Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note> namely, of one
<note n="a" place="margin">Iudg. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Micah</hi> of Ephraim, was an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that Idolatrie did ſpread thorowe the whole tribe of <hi>Dan:</hi> and ſo continued many yeares. And ſo contrarily,
<note n="b" place="margin">cap. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gideon</hi> being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp by the goodnes of God, to the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one meane familie in <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> was the cauſe of a very great deliuerance to the whole nation, from moſt mightie and cruell enemies, and moſt abominable Idolatrie, for the ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> yeares. Where were thoſe
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> King <hi>14.14.18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>7000.</hi> in the daies of <hi>Eliah,</hi> that had not bowed the knee to <hi>Baal:</hi> when he thought there were none left in Iſrael that feared God? were they not in the well inſtructed families? Whence came it that
<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. <hi>37.</hi> &amp; <hi>38.</hi> &amp; <hi>39.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his youth being ſold vnto ſtrangers, paſſed thorow ſo great temptations, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles priſon, the ſtocks &amp; iron, to be ſo worthie a father of the Common-wealth of Egypt, &amp; ſo good a nurſe to the people of God? Ica name no other outward meanes, but his good education in the familie of the faithfull. Hence is it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:
<note n="e" place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>4.13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Better is a poore and wiſe child, then an old and fooliſh king, which will no more bee admoniſhed: for out of the priſon hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth for to raigne, when hee that is borne in his kingdome is made poore.</hi> Therefore God comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth his people,
<note n="f" place="margin">Deut. <hi>11.18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to lay vp his words in their harts, and in their ſoules, &amp;c. and to teach them their children, ſpeaking of them when
<pb facs="tcp:26366:15"/>they ſit in their houſe, and when they walke by the way, and when they lye downe, and when they riſe vp, &amp;c. that their dayes may be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and the dayes of their children, &amp;c.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then what good may come out of a well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed familie, namely, that it may bee the preſeruing of the countrie and Church, in the time of extreame daunger and darknes, the ſeedplot againſt the time of reformation, and a meanes by which God doth multiplie his people and peace in a countrie: and that by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, an whole countrie may fall into Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and deſtruction. Whereby euery man may ſee what honorable ſeruice I wiſh him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when I exhort him to the inſtructing of his familie.</p>
            <p>Therefore I heartily pray and earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate all gouernours of families,
<note place="margin">A requeſt to the maſters of families.</note> that they would ſet ſuch wiſe order, in the dispoſing of all their worldly affayres, that they may haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient leiſure and quiet time for the vſe of this duetie: taking heede of all vaine excuſes,
<note place="margin">Vaine excuſes.</note> which the diuell and our corrupt nature will ſet before vs, as blockes and hinderances, that we ſhould not once meddle with ſuch
<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. <hi>10.42.</hi>
               </note> neceſſary matters. Firſt,
<note place="margin">The Lords day</note> the Lords day being an ordinary reſt &amp; time of libertie, doth call vnto you from the king of heauen, to doe this ſeruice. After morning and euening prayer, when you haue tried your people what they haue learned at the
<pb facs="tcp:26366:16"/>Church by their pastour, and called to mind the chiefe heads of his teaching: then is it good to make it a drinke offering, vpon the pastours leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; to teach them a point or two of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion.
<note place="margin">Two howers once in the weeke.</note> And if it be poſſible, I would begge for theſe poore ſoules, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, (who ſhed his precious bloud for you and them) that you would bestowe ſome two howers euery weeke, in ſome one of the working daies, (as euery man ſhalbe able to find beſt and fitteſt lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) to instruct your children and ſeruants, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of this booke, or ſome ſuch like: and that you would continue therein with al care and constancie. And I doe not doubt but you ſhall ſee great gaine by this little labour, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a bleſſing from the Lord our God,
<note n="b" place="margin">Hebr. <hi>6.10.</hi>
               </note> who will not forget any mans faithfull labour and loue, which is in Chriſt Ieſus. There are foure ſortes of people,
<note place="margin">Foure ſortes of people haue moſt fit oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to teach the yonger. 1. Noble men, &amp; Gentlemen.</note> whome I would especially moue vnto this moſt vertuous and laudable worke, for that they haue moſt fitte opportunitie, to doe greateſt ſeruice herein to God and their countrie. Firſt al noble men and Gentlemen, and all Masters of great houſholds. Whoſe families as they are the moſt in number, ſo most commonly they ſtand vnder the moſt reuerend and humble ſubmiſſion of their ſuperiours. Therefore in regard of the one they may profit moſt; and in regard of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with moſt eaſines and conueniencie;
<note place="margin">Vaine prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the greateſt part pretend it, a very hard
<pb facs="tcp:26366:16"/>thing in theſe daies, to bring their familie to Chriſtian knowledge and ſoberneſse: yet the not hauing them ſo, conſisteth not in the hardnes of the worke, or vnrulines of the people; but in the common neglect of many gouernours. Who paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ouer this dutie,
<note place="margin">Libertie the ſpoyle of the familie.</note> as a matter either not much to be regarded, or not pertaining vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: haue ſo hardeened the necks of children and ſeruants, with the looſe raines of libertie and licentiouſnes: that very few can abide this wholeſome yoake of Christian nurture, the gracious &amp; godly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of the knowledge of ſaluation.
<note place="margin">Great maſters, rulers, princes, captaines, and kings may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate families.</note> For if one man could command to feare God, &amp; to inſtruct <hi>318.</hi> able men, beſide all other ſeruants women and children: as is ſpoken of Abraham, Gene. <hi>14.14.</hi> and cap. <hi>18.19.</hi> and that a chiefe ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>120000</hi> people, could ſo gouerne his priuat familie, that he could ſay, I and mine houſe will ſerue the Lorde, as wee reade of Ioſhuah, cap. <hi>24.15.</hi> And an other great Prince had his ſeruants ſo guided in the feare of God, that hee and they were examples, in lending money and corne to the poore of the land: as did Nehemiah, cap. <hi>5.10.</hi> And if a Centurion could make both ſeruaunts and ſouldiers readie and obedient to euery good worke, as appeareth, Matth. <hi>8.9.</hi> yea if a King could proteſt vnto God, <hi>to baniſh deceitful and lying perſons out of his houſe, and to entertain the faithful, &amp; him that walketh in a perfit way:</hi> as you may ſee, Pſalm. <hi>101.5.6.</hi> I verily thinke
<pb facs="tcp:26366:17"/>that no man endowed with a good conſcience, fearing God and louing the Lord of life Ieſus Chriſt, can haue any iuſt excuſe or reaſonable pretence, to keep about him a familie vntaught in the ſweete words of the Goſpell, and the hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome paths of our bleſſed Sauiour. Except they will ſay, that it is more behoofull for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants to ſerue them, and to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them; then to ſerue and reuerence the Lord of glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Inſtructing of groat families, furthereth both Church and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note> But why ſhould I vſe many words vnto men of ſuch excellent wits &amp; great gifts, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo neceſſarily depending vpon them, that the leaſt mention ſhould ſuffice euery wiſe and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noble Gentleman to ſo glorious a worke. For by the good order &amp; Chriſtian inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one ſuch great familie, many ſoules are brought to God, there is great encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by enſample vnto others out of the familie, and a maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous power for the bringing foorth and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of al good things, both for the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and alſo for the Church of God. For hence doe all other ſortes of people take their light, and the liues of noble &amp; worſhipfull men, are many times more of force, then either the law of God or man. For they are like the great pillars in a building, that if they ſtand ſteadie in faith and good life, with their families, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are vpholden by them in the wayes of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but if they ſwarue and become careleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:26366:17"/>and diſſolute; they draw many with them, as by a mightie ſway, into the wofull downfall of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and deſtruction. Therfore aboue al men, it behooueth them to take heed to themſelues, and the good instruction and gouernment of their houſholds.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort are tutors in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to whom I ioyne alſo the third ſort,
<note place="margin">Second and third ſort, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors &amp; School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters.</note> School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in towne &amp; countrie. Which two haue a great reſemblance in their opportunitie to do good, when many mens children of all callings, are committed to their conſcience: to the one,
<note place="margin">They may doe vnſpeakable good.</note> in the firſt and more tender yeares: to the other, in the yeares of moſt danger. If theſe two ſorts of men would be painfull to wring out the iuyce of this heauenly erudition, as a neceſſary ſawce, to giue a pure verdure, to their other litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or as a ſauoury ſalt to ſeaſon al other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: it is not to be ſpoken how much good they may doe. For as young plants, being ſtraightned while they bee tender, and trimmed with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and other parts of huſbandrie, will growe very goodly to behold in their greatnes, which being neglected, are many times very crooked and vnfit for diuers vſes: So doe young men for the moſt part proue as they are nurtured in their youth. And the good instruction of Schoolemaſters and Tutors (in my knowledge) hath very well ſtraightned ſuch young impes,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:18"/>(who otherwiſe were very rough and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) that many receiue comfort by their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie example. Therefore I do moſt inſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech all Tutors and Schoolemaſters to practiſe this booke: or, becauſe you are learned, ſome better forme of your owne.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Fourthly, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing their children.</note> I doe heartily and humbly entreate all ſorts of women, to watch carefully to doe this duetie: and firſt all Ladies and Gentlewomen, that they may be honoured by the ſpirit of Ieſus Chriſt, as was that
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Ioh. Ger. <hi>1.4</hi>
               </note> elect Ladie, <hi>whoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did walke in the trueth.</hi> And all other women like
<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. <hi>16.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Perſis, who laboured much in the Lord.</hi> And as
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Sam. <hi>2.19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hannah</hi> made coates for her ſonne <hi>Samuel,</hi> who ſerued in the houſe of God: ſo theſe would aray their ſeruants and children with the
<note n="d" place="margin">Prouerb. <hi>4.9.</hi>
               </note> goodly ornaments of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, which is from aboue. A woman,
<note place="margin">Women being at hand may inſtruct their children.</note> being the
<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal <hi>128 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fruitfull vine on the houſe ſides,</hi> in whoſe ſight the
<note n="f" place="margin">Prouerb. <hi>4.3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>children are tender and deare:</hi> can by no meanes ſhew their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loue better, then being alway at hand with their children and maides, to giue them euery day in milde and pleaſant manner ſome of theſe
<note n="g" place="margin">Prou. <hi>25.12.</hi>
               </note> golden apples: wherewith the young babes will take ſuch delight, that by the nouriſhment and exerciſe thereof, they will be made
<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>8.2.</hi>
               </note> ſtrong to confound the enemies of God and their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; when they haue learned to
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Ioh. <hi>2.12.14.</hi>
               </note> know the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:18"/>and that their ſinnes are forgiuen them for Christs names ſake. It is exceeding great the profit you may doe in the familie, if as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayth of a vertuous woman, <hi>you
<note n="k" place="margin">Prou. <hi>31.26.28.</hi>
                  </note> open your mouthes in wiſedome, and the lawe of grace be in your lips:</hi> For your children <hi>ſhall riſe vp and call you bleſſed, &amp; your husbands ſhall praiſe you.</hi> Whereas
<note n="l" place="margin">chap. <hi>29.15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>children ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, make their mother aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And generally,
<note place="margin">Inſtruction of youth bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ioy to the inſtructor.</note> as a man wil ſowe his ground with the beſt ſeede, and plant his orchard with the beſt fruit; becauſe he looketh for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more gainefull encreaſe in the time of gathering: ſo if men, louing their children as well as they doe other commodities, would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo traine them vp in the beſt thinges, which are found in the diſcipline, knowledge and faith of Chriſt: they ſhould not onely eſcape many a ſecret griefe and bitter miſchiefe; but alſo bleſſe the Lord with great toyfulnes, when they finde this fruite of their education in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe good things: namely, their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to bee a comfort refreſhing and honour to their gray haires; and their ſeruants neceſſary helpes, before them, in all good cauſes and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of honestie, truth, iuſtice and mercie. For it is written as a thing that faith not,
<note n="m" place="margin">Galat. <hi>6.7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man ſoweth, that ſhall he reape.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping therefore that ſuch as bee wiſe in heart,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:19"/>will earneſtly follow my counſaile, and carefully ſtirre vp others to the ſame; I will hasten to the matter it ſelfe, by which, euery one may bee (as I hope) greatly guided in the performance of the ſame. I beſeech almightie God, of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit mercie in Ieſus Chriſt, to proſper this our godly purpoſe, to his glorie and comfort of his people. His glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name be praiſed for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfull ſeruant in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
Ioſias Nichols.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:20"/>
            <head>The Booke to the <hi>Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>COme buy me, but paſſe not by me,</l>
               <l>for by me thou ſhalt winne,</l>
               <l>To light thy people, by my light:</l>
               <l>to trauell light, from ſinne.</l>
               <l>The word, with words of trueth and ioy,</l>
               <l>doth ſhew his word by me:</l>
               <l>A way (which if thou way) it waies</l>
               <l>thee to felicitie.</l>
               <l>Two houres, each weeke, ſixe monthes, to ſtay</l>
               <l>with thee, no more, I begge:</l>
               <l>To ſtay thy people, on that ſtay,</l>
               <l>which hell gates cannot wagge.</l>
               <l>Then trie, how trie my triall is:</l>
               <l>if God doe helpe with grace;</l>
               <l>Both man and child, as wit doth grow,</l>
               <l>ſhall ſee the heauenly place.</l>
               <l>Yet know, that knowledge and no more,</l>
               <l>by thee, to thine I giue:</l>
               <l>The ſpirit of Chriſt (pray thou therefore)</l>
               <l>workes faith; that thou maiſt liue:</l>
               <l>And as by proofe, thou proues me true,</l>
               <l>to proue the thing I ſay:</l>
               <l>So double time, for double gaine,</l>
               <l>and grant me longer ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="instruction">
            <pb facs="tcp:26366:20"/>
            <head>An order of houſhold <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by which euery master</hi> of a familie, may eaſilie and in ſhort ſpace, make his whole houſhold vnderſtand the principall and chiefe poyntes <hi>of Christian religion: without the knowledge whereof no man can be ſaued.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The firſt booke.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 1. <hi>The first order of instruction.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this order, ſome things are for the young &amp; tender yeres, and ſome for yeres of greater capacitie, for confirmation and helpes: till they may bee grounded in the principles, with good vnderſtanding, to giue a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their faith by the holy Scriptures. Firſt, from the time that children ſpeake, it is good to drop in this good licour of heauenly doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.
<pb facs="tcp:26366:21"/>For as Salomon ſaith:
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Teach a childe the trade of his waye, and when hee is olde hee ſhall not depart from it.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt order from the time that children can ſpeake.</note> Therefore from that time, it ſhall bee good to teach them (as the manner of all chriſtians is) to ſay without book diſtinctly: <hi>The Lords prayer, the Creede and the ten Commaundements.</hi> And as hee perceiueth their capacitie to growe, to droppe into them by familiar wordes, the name of God, how hee made vs: the name of Chriſt, how hee ſhed his blood for vs: the name of the holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth vs; and that there is but one God and three perſons, &amp;c. Alſo the name of death, that for ſinne all men die: and the name of the reſurrection, that through Chriſt we ſhall liue againe in heauen: alwaies applying himſelfe with tearmes to their capacitie: and alluring the childe, to the feeling and loue of God, of Chriſt, and of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; and to the hatred of ſinne: as by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cauſing the childe to ſay: <hi>God loueth vs, for he made vs, and giueth vs all things, as our meate, drinke, apparell, &amp;c. God loueth vs, for he gaue Chriſt to die for our ſoules. God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs, for he giueth vs life after we he dead, in heauen. We muſt not doe ſinne and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for it bringeth paine, ſicknes, death, &amp;c.</hi> Then the capacitie encreaſing, make them pronounce, how many petitions in the Lords praier, and which they be: how many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements &amp; which they be, til they can tell you
<pb facs="tcp:26366:21"/>euery one, being asked ſodainely out of order, as the tenth, the fourth, the ſeuenth, &amp;c. After that they haue been thus trayned a while, and can anſwer as children, readily to theſe: then let them learne that ſhort Catechiſme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out booke, which beginneth after this ſorte. <hi>Who made thee? God. What is God? he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, &amp;c. Wherefore did he make thee? to ſerue him, &amp;c.</hi> Which may be bought for the valew of a pennie in the bookeſellers ſhops.</p>
                  <p>After all this, teach them ſome ſhort ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſentences of holy Scripture: ſtories ſuch as theſe, Gen. 4. verſ. 2. the trade, ſacrifice and death of Abel, Gen. 11.1. the building and ouerthrow of Babel. Mark. 10.13. Chriſt receiueth children and bleſſeth them. Now ſome ſtories may bee taught them worde for worde, as in the text, ſuch is that of Eliſha, 2. King. 2. verſ. 23.24. onely adding the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets name, which is verſe 22. and in the end of this ſtorie teach them the vſe. <hi>Children may not mocke.</hi> Some ſtories muſt be gathered more ſhort, then the text, as that of Dinah, Gen. 34. <hi>Dinah the daughter of Iacob, went out to ſee the maides of the countrie; and one Shechem, ſonne of Hamor Lord of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, ſaw her, and defiled her, and for this cauſe Simeon and Leui, ſlew Shechem and all the towne with the edge of the ſworde. The vſe, Maides muſt not wander or goe a gadding.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:22"/>The ſentences may be ſuch as theſe are, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs 29.15. <hi>The rod and correction giue wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but a childe ſet at libertie, maketh his mother aſhamed,</hi> Mark. 8.36. <hi>What ſhall it profit a man, though hee ſhould win the whole world, if he looſe his owne ſoule,</hi> Luk. 9.10. <hi>The ſonne of man is come to ſeeke and to ſaue that which is loſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then teach them an enſample of euerie commaundement to the ſence of this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>The firſt commaundement brake Ahab, taking Baal for his God, 1. King. 18.21. or 1. King. 16.31.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond, Ieroboam that worſhipped golden calues, 1. King. 12.28.</p>
                  <p>The third, an Iſraelitiſh womans ſonne, ſtriuing with a man of Iſrael, blaſphemed the name of the Lord and curſed, Leuit. 24.10.11.</p>
                  <p>The fourth, one that gathered ſticks on the Sabbath day, Numb. 15.32.</p>
                  <p>The fift, Abſalom, who rebelled againſt his father, 2. Sam. 15.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt, Cain, who ſlew Abel, Gen. 4.8.</p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth, a Leuites Concubine, who played the whore, Iudg. 19.1.2.</p>
                  <p>The eyght, the Shabeans tooke away Iobs oxen and aſſes, Iob. 1.14.15.</p>
                  <p>Ninth, Potiphars wife falſely accuſed Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Gen. 39.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:22"/>
Tenth, Ahab luſteth for Naboths vineyard, 1. King. 21.2.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe it will not bee amiſſe to cauſe the learner to repeate without booke, the places where all the ſtories and ſentences are written: and herein the teacher may vſe his diſcretion, to teach them more or leſſe of like ſort and eaſines: ſo that hee ouercharge them not at any one time: but let them as it were creepe vpon them by often repeating: and he ſhall finde that a little childe will beare very much more, then a man that hath not tried would beleeue. And if he cauſe them to learne without booke, the 1.15.112.127. and 128. Pſalmes, or ſome of them, they will no doubt worke very godly impreſſions in the tender minds. And it is a good recreation to quicken them, to teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſing ſome ſhort pſalmes, as the 117. the 131.133. and ſuch like, as they are in Engliſh meter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 2. <hi>The ſecond order of inſtruction, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the vnderſtanding.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">This order is beſt, from ſixe yeare olde and vpwards, &amp; in ſome capacities before, and for ſuch as are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of what age ſo euer.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that they can handſomely do theſe things; then this catechiſme following will be moſt neceſſarie for the opening of their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: where the maſter of the houſe muſt
<pb facs="tcp:26366:23"/>not binde the learner to the very words (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) here ſet downe: but ſo teach, as euery time he repeateth any queſtion, there may bee ſome little difference in his wordes. And for that cauſe I will ſhewe him diuers formes of ſpeaking, (in ſome of the moſt needefull pointes) teaching the meaning of one poynt, which a childe or young man will quickelie conceiue, and by the variation be able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and beare away, and to anſwer with his own words, in diuers ſortes, at diuers times and all to one ſenſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="catechism">
                  <head>The Catechiſme for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond order.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <p>Or thus: <hi>How many Gods are there?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But one only and three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c.</p>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>VVHat thinkeſt thou of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I beleeue there is one God, and three perſons, God the Father, God the Sonne and God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Was there not a time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor earth? &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Yea: <hi>How did they begin?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>God created them by his word, &amp;c.</p>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>How came the World?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God made all things, of nothing in ſixe dayes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In what day made he man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſixt day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was the woman made the ſame daye?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Both man and woman were made in one daye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:23"/>
                     <hi>How were they made?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God made man of the duſt of the grounde, and breathed in his face the breath of life, and the man was a liuing ſoule, that is, a liuely creature hauing bodie and ſoule. After God caſt Adam into an heauie ſleepe, and tooke out one of his ribbes, and cloſed vp the fleſh, and of that rib, hee made the woman, ſo there was man and woman: the mans name was Adam, and the womans Eue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was man made any whit more excellent then other creatures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yes, in two things: he was made after Gods image, and clothed with happines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What was that image of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Knowledge, holines, and righteouſnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What was the happines?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He was made Lord ouer the creatures, and being naked, was not aſhamed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What did God with man after hee had thus made him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee ſet him in a moſt pleaſant place of the world, called the garden of Eden, appoynted him to keepe and dreſſe the garden, gaue him leaue to eate of all the trees in the garden, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one, called <hi>The tree of knowledge of good and euill:</hi> and if he eate of that tree, he ſhould die the death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What death?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:24"/>
Of bodie and ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was there not another tree of ſpeciall name?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yes, the tree of life which was a Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſigne, that if man continued in his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes, he ſhould liue for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>If Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made good and happie: how came wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>By eating the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruit, ſinne, ſhame, damnation and all other miſeries came vpon man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Did man continue in his vprightnes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No, for the diuell abuſing the bodie of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, tempted the woman Eue, and ſhee did eate of the forbidden fruite, and ſhe gaue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and he did eate, and then they were aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And ſo Adam and Eue, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde were dead in ſinne, and vnder damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bodie and ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">How ſhall we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> deliuered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>How ſhall we eſcape ſinne and damnation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Onely by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>leefe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                              <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> was he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>man?</hi> Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ngin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>If Mary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er, who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>?</hi> He as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uching his Godhead, and ſhe touching his manhood.</note> 
                     <hi>What is Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He is the eternall ſonne of God made man, that is, perfect God and perfect man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What did he for vs to ſaue our ſoules?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee died and ſhed his moſt precious blood to redeeme vs from our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is it not poſſible for a man to liue ſo iuſtly and vprightly, that he may
<note n="g" place="margin">Deſerue or merit.</note> obtaine his owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by well doing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No man hath ſuch a gift or power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe no man can keepe al the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God: if we breake any one we be guiltie of all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:24"/>
                     <hi>How ſhall we doe then?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All doe not beleeue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What neede we then care to do
<note n="h" place="margin">To liue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly or godly</note> good works?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We muſt doe good works, becauſe they are commanded by God; and it is our duetie to obey him that made and ſaued vs: wee ought to bee thankefull and to glorifie him, and to declare our faith by our workes, for the good enſample of others, and for many other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie vſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How are we ſaued by Chriſt, ſeeing we die daylie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This bodily death, is but the parting of the ſoule from the bodie for a time, but the bodie ſhall riſe againe, euen as Chriſt roſe the third day, for at the laſt day, when Chriſt ſhall come againe to iudge the quicke and the dead, all that beleeue in him ſhall riſe againe vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, and all other to euerlaſting damnation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How come we to know theſe things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God ſendeth his word to bee preached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe all beleeue who heare the worde?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>None but they, whoſe hearts are opened, by his holy ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are there no other helps of
<note n="i" place="margin">Beleeſe.</note> faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:25"/>
Many: as the experience of all Gods doings according to his word, and namely in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the exerciſe of all good works: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the right vſe of the ſeales of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which are commonly called Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which be they?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Baptiſme and the Lords Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is to be ſeene in them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The outward ſigne as water, bread, and wine, and the ſignification which is the
<note n="*" place="margin">The death or promiſe of Chriſt, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death.</note> grace of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore bee children baptized with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In token that their ſinnes are waſhed away by the blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why doe men receiue the bread and wine in the Communion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In token that Chriſt gaue his bodie and blood for our redemption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are they onely tokens or bare ſignes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No: they are alſo as ſeales to aſſure vs of the grace of Chriſt, and his laſt will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How doe Baptiſme and the Lordes ſupper differ?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Baptiſme is outwardly with water, and the Lordes Supper with bread and wine: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Baptiſme ſignifieth the waſhing of our ſinnes, to enter vs into the Church: the Lords Supper is for the ſtrengthening of our faith:
<pb facs="tcp:26366:25"/>thirdly, Baptiſme is once, ſignifying that wee which are by nature, the children of wrath are once borne in Chriſt, to be Gods children: but the Lords Supper is often, ſignifying by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bread and drinking wine, the davly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of our faith in and by Chriſt, that wee may continually grow ſtronger and ſtronger vnto eternall life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is eternall life?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To liue with God, and to bee partakers of his glorie for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 3. <hi>The third order of teaching.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEre followeth diuers Catechiſmes for confirmation of knowledge,
<note place="margin">This order is for all that can conceiue well of the former, how young or olde ſoeuer they be: but in common and meaner capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities from 8. yeares and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> drawne out of the words of ſome place of holy Scripture. Where I muſt admoniſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſter or teacher in the familie, to follow this order. Firſt, to teach his people, perfectly and diſtinctly to ſaye the place of Scripture without booke: which being perfect to ſhew them the briefe meaning; and then the ſeuerall poynts of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and how they bee gathered out of the text. For which cauſe he ſhall finde, the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other textes and notes in the margin, for his help and direction, which he muſt keep to himſelfe, and giue them the meaning or ſubſtance onely. Yet if he once get his family
<pb facs="tcp:26366:26"/>to conceiue deeper, hee may acquainte them with all; but he muſt take heede hee oppreſſe not their memories, with ouer much at once, but giue them more or leſſe, as hee perceiueth them able to conceiue and beare away, and to remember at the next time; for it is very needefull to repeate that which was firſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, before he begin any more. Therefore for a while, after they can ſaye the place without booke, and ſhew where it is written, what chapter, what verſe and the meaning, let them haue onely ſome two or three poyntes: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a while, hee ſhall perceiue, that by vſe they will bee able to take a great deale more, euen an whole Catechiſme at once; yea and by often practiſe to gather ſome poyntes of themſelues: yet muſt hee not ceaſe going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, becauſe that the
<note n="k" place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.1.</note> oftener, the ſafer it is, and happier for them to bee grounded. Now as ofte as they haue learned any one Catechiſme thorough out, cauſe them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat all that whole Catechiſme together, as the place of Scripture, the meaning, all the poyntes of doctrine, and how they are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the text; and after (but not before) begin the next Catechiſme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="catechism">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26366:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The first Catechiſme for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of knowledge, is drawne out of this text or place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi>
                     </bibl> I will put enmitie betweene thee and the woman, and betweene thy ſeede and her ſeede; he ſhall breake thine head, and thou ſhalt
<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. <hi>breake.</hi>
                     </note> bruiſe his heele.</q>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The interpretation or meaning.</head>
                     <p>THe Maſter muſt conſider out of the text,
<note place="margin">This is for the maſters helpe.</note> that the diuell abuſed the bodie of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to deceiue Euah: &amp; therefore the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is pronounced vpon the ſerpent, which partly and eſpecially is in the words going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but although he ſpeak to the ſerpent, yet theſe
<note n="l" place="margin">As theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces expound, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 27.1. <hi>Micah.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 91.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.18.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. <hi>&amp; Reuel.</hi> 12.7.8.9.10.</note> wordes are properly to bee applyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the diuell himſelfe, whoſe inſtrument the ſerpent was, (although they haue accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, euen againſt the beaſt it ſelfe, in that hee is hated naturally of all mankinde) therefore the Maſter hauing wayed the places in the margin, may giue his familie this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation following.</p>
                     <p>By the ſerpent and his ſeede,
<note place="margin">This is for the familie.</note> is meant Satan and his members, wicked men: by the ſeede of the woman, is ment Chriſt and his members;
<pb facs="tcp:26366:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:28"/>by breaking of head and heele, is meant that either ſhall wound each other, but the diuell ſhall bee vanquiſhed. The meaning is then, that God will haue this to bee a puniſhment of the diuell; that he ſhould haue continuall warre with Chriſt and his Saints, and finally be ouercome, and all that take his part:</p>
                     <p>Out of which interpretation ariſe theſe poynts of Catechiſme.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="points_of_doctrine">
                     <head>The poynts of doctrine.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the text, which incluſiuely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his ſinne, to haue an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to him &amp; his ſeede for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</note> By the temptation of the ſerpent the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and Satanas, man became a great ſinner, and ſubiect to great miſerie.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">This fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of the former, and is ſhewed, cap. 1. and 2.</note> Man was made good, without ſinne and miſerie, before this temptation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Becauſe the wordes are the indivial ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God to that purpoſe, and is to expounded, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44.47. <hi>Acts.</hi> 13.10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3.4. cap. 11.13.14. <hi>Eph</hi> 2 1. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.10.</note> God hath decreed, what ſhall bee the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Satan and mankinde, namely, that ſome men ſhall be the ſeede of Satan and the children of perdition: and ſome with Chriſt conquerers of them both.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">So expounded, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</note> Here the perſon of Chriſt is declared, that he is, as all other men, the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is, the ſonne of God made man.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">Expreſſed in the meaning, and is ſeene in Caine, and all of like ſort following.</note> There ſhall be alway enmitie of Sathan and his members, againſt Chriſt and his members.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:28"/>
6.
<note n="6" place="margin">This is the breaking of the heele, as appeareth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay.</hi> 53.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. <hi>chap.</hi> 6.4.5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.19 20. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.9.</note> Great ſorrowes, temptations and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, in bodie, goods, name and life come vnto Chriſt &amp; his members by Satan and his members.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.
<note n="7" place="margin">This is the breaking of the ſerpents head, &amp; is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> By the death of Chriſt and all the parts of his mediation, hee for vs and wee thorow him doe ouercome the diuel: to the reſtoring of the bodie in the reſurrection of life, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing with immortall riches both bodie and ſoule, in the ſaluation of all beleeuers.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.
<note n="8" place="margin">Plaine in the words, and is expounded, 2. <hi>Corint.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.6 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4.</note> The duetie of all Chriſtian beleeuers is to reſiſt the diuell and his members, and to haue no fellowſhip with the workes of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 4. <hi>The ſecond Catechiſme for confirmation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="quotation">
                     <head>The Text.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Gen. 12.3.</hi>
                        </bibl> In thee ſhall all families of the earth be bleſſed.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The Interpretation.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">For the maſter</note> THeſe words containe Gods promiſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the bleſſed ſeede made vnto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, when he called him to be his childe and father of the faithfull, which
<note n="m" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> before was ſpoken in generall hard to bee knowne, but here is ſhewed more plaine and eaſie to bee found by the particular, namely, that it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:26366:29"/>be in Abrahams ſtocke and linage.</p>
                     <p>This clauſe,
<note place="margin">For the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</note> in thee, is to be vnderſtood of Abrahams
<note n="n" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.17. <hi>and Gal.</hi> 3.16.</note> ſeede which is Chriſt (who after a ſort was in him, that is, in his loynes.) By <hi>all families,</hi> is meant
<note n="o" place="margin">
                           <hi>Act</hi> 3.25. <hi>&amp; Galat.</hi> 3.6.</note> all nations as well Iewes as Gentiles. And by <hi>bleſſed,</hi> is meant the
<note n="p" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal</hi> 3.13.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.13. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.1.</note> deliuerance from the curſed and damnable eſtate, wherein we were by Adams fall. The ſumme is: God doth promiſe that both Iewes and Gentiles ſhall haue ſaluation, in none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but in Chriſt, who as touching his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was Abrahams ſeede.</p>
                     <p>This teacheth eſpecially two ſorts of points:
<list>
                           <item>What wee are of ourſelues.</item>
                           <item>What wee are made by Chriſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrines">
                     <head>The doctrines.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">Otherwiſe there needed not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.2</note> Of ourſelues wee are ſinners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accurſed to damnation, by Adams fall.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">This is in a manner the text.</note> By Chriſt wee are made bleſſed, that is, heires of eternall life.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.</note> Here is taught what Chriſt is touching his perſon (as in the former Catechiſme) Chriſt is God and man of the ſeede of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">Theſe two are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of this text. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.12.23.24.</note> There is but one way of ſaluation which is common to Iew and Gentill.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">Theſe two are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of this text. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.12.23.24.</note> Chriſt is applied vnto vs for iuſtification by no meanes but faith onely.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:29"/>
6.
<note n="6" place="margin">So gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.18.</note> Our ſaluation commeth not of workes in our doing, or will in our chooſing, but of Gods free promiſe.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Vnder this word <hi>bleſsed,</hi>
                        <note n="7" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.6.</note> are contained all Gods graces and gifts, which thorough Chriſt hee giueth to his Church, and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection in this life, with the reſurrection vnto life eternall.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. One part of this bleſſednes is,
<note n="8" place="margin">So applied <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.73. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.25.26.</note> that Chriſt turneth vs from our ſinnes, and leadeth vs by the promiſe to walke in godlines and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.
<note n="9" place="margin">For this promiſe is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiue, as <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18.</note> There is no other meanes of ſaluation but Chriſt, and therefore all other profeſſions and religions, which teach not the true beleefe in Chriſt, are the ſynagogues of Satan, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of hell fire.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.
<note n="10" place="margin">Ancienter by 430 yeares then the law of works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.9.</note> That we are iuſtified and ſaued by faith onely, is the moſt ancient doctrine, being taught by God vnto Abraham, long before euer there was any Church of Rome.</p>
                     <p>Here the maſter of the familie, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie vnto euery particular perſon, how his faith ſhould agree with theſe points by the example of Iob, whoſe Creede thus followeth.</p>
                     <p>Iob. 19.25. <hi>I am ſure my redeemer liueth, &amp;c.</hi> Where thou maiſt ſee his faith, in that he
<pb facs="tcp:26366:30"/>ſaith, <hi>I am ſure;</hi> his acknowledgement of ſins, and expectation of Chriſt in the word <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and in the word, <hi>liueth,</hi> hee ſheweth that Chriſt is alway the onely
<note n="q" place="margin">So expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24.25.</note> ſufficient fauiour; his hope of the reſurrection is plaine in the reſt, and the deſcription of eternall life in this,
<note n="r" place="margin">So defined, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.15.</note> 
                        <hi>he ſhall ſee God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 5. <hi>The third Catechiſme for confirmation in knowledge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="quotation">
                     <head>The place of Scripture.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Eſay. 53.11.</hi>
                        </bibl> By his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſeruant, iuſtifie many: whoſe iniquities he ſhal beare.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The Interpretation.</head>
                     <p>THeſe words are euidently a propheſie of Chriſt Ieſus, wherin the maſter muſt teach his familie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the perſons. Firſt he that ſpeaketh is God: then the perſons of whom he ſpeaketh are two, 1. Chriſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he calleth his righteous ſeruant: 2. all beleeuers, which are many men and women whoſe ſinnes hee beareth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <head>The Doctrine.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">In the firſt perſon. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</note> God decreeth the ſaluation of many by Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:30"/>
2. Mans works, free-will,
<note n="2" place="margin">This fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of the firſt.</note> merit and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction are excluded, by the vndeſired and vndeſerued good pleaſure of GOD in ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. In Chriſt we ſee two things,
<note n="3" place="margin">This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the two following</note> what hee is in himſelfe, and what to vs: the firſt we call his perſon, and the ſecond his office, adioyned to his perſon.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In his perſon hee is called: <hi>a ſeruant,
<note n="4" place="margin">In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon.</note> Gods ſeruant, and a iuſt ſeruant. A ſeruant,</hi> becauſe being God he became a man, which is called the
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                           <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> 
                        <hi>forme of a ſeruant: Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant;</hi> becauſe hee came to doe
<note n="t" place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.7.</note> Gods will. <hi>Just or righteous,</hi> becauſe it behoued, that hee being
<note n="u" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</note> iuſt ſhould die for vs, who are vniuſt: ſo that he being
<note n="x" place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14.15.</note> GOD, was alſo man in all thing ſauing ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">In that God aſſigneth and accepteth him to iuſtifie vs, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.6.</note> His office is here generally to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betweene God and man.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The parts of his office,
<note n="6" place="margin">This is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the two following. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 110.</note> are
<list>
                           <item>his Kingdome.</item>
                           <item>his Prieſthood.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7. He being King of his Church, giueth giftes, that is, Miniſters to teach remiſſion of ſinnes, and ſo as the righteous King he iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all beleeuers.
<note n="7" place="margin">In theſe words by his knowledge ſhal, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.33. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.9.10.11</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. Hee being Prieſt, beareth our ſinnes,
<note n="8" place="margin">So expounded. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11.12.</note> when he made himſelfe a liuely ſacrifice to his father for vs.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:31"/>
9.
<note n="9" place="margin">This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth the former two, &amp; in them is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: reade 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.20.21. <hi>&amp; Rom.</hi> 4.25. <hi>and cap.</hi> 10.4.14.</note> By his Prieſthoode he performeth the worke of our righteouſnes, and by his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office hee applieth it vnto vs. For being Prieſt he dieth for our ſins, and riſeth to make vs righteous: but yet till by hearing this kings Embaſſadors wee doe beleeue, wee are not iuſtified.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.
<note n="10" place="margin">In the third perſon: Many, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.24.25.</note> Wee are of our owne nature ſinners, and al our iuſtification and redemption com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth onely by the free will of God, thorow beleefe in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.
<note n="11" place="margin">Reade <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7.</note> Vnder iuſtification is contained glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification or euerlaſting life, for theſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie follow each other.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.
<note n="12" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4.</note> If Chriſt iuſtifie vs by bearing our ſinnes, then wee muſt knowe, that aboue all things we ought to flie ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Here the Maſter of the familie may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to his people in a ſhort ſumme, the ſubſtance of this Catechiſme, by the words of Habbakuck. cap. 2. ver. 4.</hi> The iuſt ſhall liue by his faith.</p>
                     <p>In regarde of iuſtification thus,
<note n="y" place="margin">So expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17 <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.11.</note> a good man findeth in himſelfe, no wiſdome, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, power, will or workes to leane vnto: but looketh for his iuſtification and ſaluation onely by faith in Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:31"/>
In regarde of ſanctification thus:
<note n="z" place="margin">So opened, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38.39 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19.20.</note> A good man forſaketh all his owne earthly deuiſes, and all wicked workes, in the maintaining of his eſtate and life, beleeuing that his life ſhall bee maintayned without any euill deuiſes or ſhiftes, and therefore committeth his ſoule, life, and all hee hath into Gods hands, in wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dooing, depending vpon the mercie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God in Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 6. <hi>The fourth Catechiſme, for confirmation of knowledge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="quotation">
                     <head>The place of holy Scripture.</head>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Pſalme. 130.3.</hi>
                           </bibl> If thou O Lorde ſtreightly markeſt iniquities: O Lorde who ſhall ſtand.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>4.</hi>
                           </bibl> But mercie is with thee that thou maieſt be feared.</p>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The Interpretation.</head>
                     <p>THis text is a confeſſion of faith, agreeing in ſubſtance with the former, wherein the faithfull ſoule, applieth the doctrine of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation vnto a ſpeciall vſe in prayer, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning two parts, what wee are without Chriſt, (for he is the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7.</note> mercie ſeate) and what wee are by Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:32"/>
                     <head>The Doctrine.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">Marke ſtreightly.</note> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſtand before God to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, if God ſhould iudge him after his ſins.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">Mercie.</note> It is his mercy applyed vnto vs by faith in Chriſt Ieſus, by which we ſtand iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Feare thee.</note> No man can feare God, that is to ſaye, ſerue God, as his childe, vnleſſe hee bee ſet free by his mercie.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">Stand. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.2.</note> To ſtand, is to be in ſtate of grace, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hope of the glorie of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And here the Maſter of the familie may doe well to ſhew vnto his folke, how the Scriptures of
<note n="a" place="margin">
                              <hi>Luk</hi> 24.44.</note> Moſes, the Prophets and Pſalmes, doe agree in one ſweete harmonie, teaching one and the ſame doctrine of ſaluation and godlynes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.14.</note> faith and loue which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 7.</head>
                  <p>Now here follow a few more, for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their knowledge and faith, out of the new teſtament.</p>
                  <div type="quotation">
                     <head>The fift Catechiſme for cleerenes of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</head>
                     <head type="sub">The Text.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Matth. 17.5.</hi>
                        </bibl> This is my beloued ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed: heare him.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:32"/>
                     <head>The interpretation.</head>
                     <p>THeſe wordes are the voyce,
<note place="margin">For the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, reade 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> which Peter Iames and Iohn heard in the mount, to come from heauen, where Chriſt receiued of God the father, honour &amp; glorie, when there came ſuch a voyce vnto him, from the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent glorie. Which thing if the Maſter tell his familie, and demaunde of them, firſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as they haue learned by other places; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, what poyntes of doctrine they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in it; it may bee they will bee found by meanes of the former to doe much in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very eaſy.
<note place="margin">For the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</note> How be it to vnderſtand it three things muſt be found out: firſt, who ſpake the words, that is, God the father, teſtifying of his ſonne, teacheth the ſumme of the Goſpell: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, what is ment by this clauſe, <hi>In whom, whom</hi> ſignifieth Chriſt; and <hi>In,</hi> ſignifieth ſuch as by beleefe are
<note n="a" place="margin">So is the clauſe vſed, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.6. <hi>and Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>and</hi> 5.1.</note> in him: thirdly, what is ment by this clauſe, <hi>I am well pleaſed</hi> which I take to be, that God hath
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp; Ioh.</hi> 1.12.13.</note> decreede in himſelfe to engraft all his elect into Chriſt by faith, and ſo to be well pleaſed with them, being planted by beleefe in Chriſt. The ſubſtance then is, that God would haue all men know, this man Chriſt, who was now in the mount with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Iames, and Iohn, to bee his beloued ſonne, and that he hath purpoſed to accept of euery ſoule that ſhould beleeue in him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commandeth all to heare and obey him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:33"/>
                     <head>The Doctrine or Catechiſme.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">This is all the text, and is proued, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.</note> The Goſpell conſiſteth in the true knowledge of the perſon and office of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The doctrine of his perſon is cleere, in that the father calleth this man Chriſt his ſonne: ſo that hee is the ſonne of God and man. Where this worde <hi>Sonne,</hi> is not to bee vnderſtoode in regarde of creation, as was
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.38.</note> Adam, or of adoption, as the
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.16.</note> elect: but by
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.18.</note> nature and generation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Obſerue: the diſtinct perſon of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, acknowledgeth the diſtinct perſon of the ſonne: to which adde out of Matth. 3.17. the diſtinct perſon of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">
                           <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 8.30.31. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14.16.</note> This ſonne is called beloued, to ſhew, that in the loue, the father hath to the ſonne, there flow the ioyfull ſtreames of loue vnto his elect: ſo that hee is the fountaine of grace vnto vs.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Vnto theſe two poyntes of his perſon are ioyned two of his office, anſwering vnto them: Firſt, in the beloued he is well pleaſed: this ſheweth the mediation of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to GOD for vs: Secondly, him being ſonne he would haue heard: this ſheweth the mediation of his ſoueraigne kingdome, from the father, ouer vs.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.
<note n="6" place="margin">Expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.21.</note> The mediation of his Prieſthoode: that God will haue him come betweene vs and
<pb facs="tcp:26366:33"/>himſelfe; that our ſinnes whereof we are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in our ſelues, being pardoned through him, wee might haue his euerlaſting fauour vnto ſaluation.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. This mediation is to be vnderſtoode in the parts: firſt, that Chriſt died for our ſinnes,
<note n="1" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25.</note> and roſe againe to make vs righteous: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note n="2" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</note> by this meanes hee bringeth vs to God: thirdly, ſetteth vs at peace with him,
<note n="3" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.2.</note> that wee may haue acceſſe thorow him to his grace, wherein wee ſtand reioycing vnder the hope of the glorie of God: fourthly,
<note n="4" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.2.</note> hee is gone vp into heauen to prepare a place for vs: fiftly,
<note n="5" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.</note> hee ſitteth there as our aduocate.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.
<note n="8" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25.</note> In that hee decreeth to pleaſe himſelfe with Chriſt: this ſheweth our free election, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, iuſtification, and ſaluation, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all mans merits, free-will, workes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene, and all the reprobate: and to eſtabliſh an vnſpeakeable comfort to the man, who findeth that God hath giuen him faith, that hee may knowe, that GOD hath
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.40.</note> predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated him vnto ſaluation in his beloued ſonne.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>In him,</hi>
                        <note n="9" place="margin">God ſpake this, &amp; he will reproue them that put any thing to his word. <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.5.6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note> excludeth vnbeleeuers from this mediation, it condemneth all other ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and additaments whatſoeuer, as ſtubble for the fire.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. The ſecond parte of his office is his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie, in this, <hi>Heare him,</hi> which ſheweth
<pb facs="tcp:26366:34"/>his ſoueraigne authoritie ouer
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8.9.</note> all nations: which is, that he is the chiefe
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.</note> Prophet ouer all: chiefe or
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.</note> hye Prieſt: and eſpecially
<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.21.22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.16.</note> King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all Kings, powers, and principalizies, and in all things head to his Church.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.
<note n="11" place="margin">This ſo taught <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.18.</note> Vnder this word, <hi>Heare,</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our obedience, that we ſhould heare him, which is with our eares, heartes, and deedes, that is, by learning his word, by acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, by faith, and practiſing it by works.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.
<note n="12" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.21. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.8. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9.10. <hi>&amp;c. and cap.</hi> 9.24.25.</note> This word, <hi>him,</hi> is ſpoken excluſiuely, that is: there is no other head of the Church to rule and make lawes, but Chriſt: no other maſter to teach and preſcribe doctrine; no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prieſt to offer, or ſatisfie by ſacrifice.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 8. <hi>The ſixt Catechiſme, for increaſe of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="quotation">
                     <head>The place of Scripture.</head>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iohn. 3.16.</hi>
                        </bibl> God ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his only begotten ſonne; that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The Interpretation.</head>
                     <p>IN this verſe,
<note place="margin">Let the maſter ſhewe all this interpretation to his familie, and cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhew it him againe.</note> Chriſt teacheth Nichodemus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many other argumentes, to vnderſtand the doctrine of regeneration, ſpoken of verſ. 3.
<pb facs="tcp:26366:34"/>by the cauſe, namely, by the firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall cauſe, which is
<note n="a" place="margin">God.</note> God: in whom there is rehearſed no
<note n="b" place="margin">So loued.</note> outwarde cauſe to moue him, but onely that of his owne goodnes his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular loue did this worke, namely, hee loued
<note n="c" place="margin">The world.</note> the world, which by no meanes had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it. The greatnes of which loue is ſhewed by the
<note n="d" place="margin">He gaue.</note> worke, that <hi>he gaue his ſonne,</hi> not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by any prayers, merits, or rewarde of ours, but of his free gift. And
<note n="e" place="margin">His ſonne.</note> what gaue he? the earth, the heauen, cattell, infinit trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, heauenly ſpirits? Nothing ſo: yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that which excelleth al theſe things, euen his <hi>ſonne.</hi> And what
<note n="f" place="margin">Onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</note> ſonne? an adopted ſonne, or counterfeit ſonne? No: but his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten ſonne. And
<note n="g" place="margin">Not periſh, but haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</note> why did hee giue him? that we ſhould beſtow any thing vpon him, or that wee can doe any thing for him? Leaſt of all: but that he might deliuer vs from euerlaſting perdition, and giue vs eternall life. Vpon what
<note n="h" place="margin">Whoſoeuer beleeueth in l.im.</note> condition? that we ſhould do all his lawe, and ſatisfie by contrition, pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or workes of condignitie, or ſupererro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? No ſuch thing: but <hi>whoſoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him.</hi> So that wee with Nichodemus may learne, that God giuing his ſonne of his ſingular loue doth work this new birth, when by the preaching of the Goſpell, the ſpirit fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in vs faith in Chriſt, and when by faith he maketh vs partakers of euerlaſting ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:35"/>then doe we enter into the kingdome of heauen. And ſo it is expounded by the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.6.7.</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: <hi>God of his mercie ſaueth vs by the new birth, which is ſhed vpon vs thorow Chriſt, that being iustified by his grace, wee may bee made heires thorow hope of eternall life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now there are in theſe wordes certaine things to bee further explaned: that ſeeing their meaning more cleerely, wee may more fitly gather out the ſeuerall braunches of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Firſt in this word
<note n="*" place="margin">Loued, what.</note> 
                        <hi>loued,</hi> I vnderſtand the goodnes of God according to his eternall decree, which is called
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
                        <hi>The good pleaſure of his will.</hi> As the
<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.10.</note> Prophet alſo ſayth: <hi>The Lord would breake him, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this word
<note n="*" place="margin">World, what.</note> world, for the vniuerſall and whole mankinde, according to the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God made vnto
<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> Abraham, namely, that hee loued both Iewes and Gentiles, as is plainly taught, Rom. 3.29.30. Yet
<note n="e" place="margin">Reade <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.14.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7.8. <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.34.35.43.</note> euery particular and ſinguler perſon is not meant thereby: as Chriſt expoundeth himſelfe, when he addeth this limitation, that <hi>whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, this word
<note n="*" place="margin">Periſh, what.</note> periſh, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the miſerable condition of mankinde in himſelfe by ſinne: yet when hee ſayth, <hi>ſhould not periſh,</hi> he meaneth not that in this world wee ſhould not dye for a time, but that
<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11 25.26</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we be dead, we ſhould be quickened and riſe againe vnto eternall life. Neither doe
<pb facs="tcp:26366:35"/>I thinke, that this bodily death is that death which was threatned to
<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</note> Adam, which is properly the death
<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.</note> in ſinne, and to bee ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from the preſence of God, as was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Gen. 3. Therefore this is our life to bee
<note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</note> brought by Chriſt vnto GOD, to
<note n="k" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</note> enioy whoſe preſence is euerlaſting life it ſelfe. The ſumme then is this: The free good will of God hath giuen his onely begotten ſonne vnto all mankinde, that, whomſoeuer hee by his ſpirit, thorow hearing the Goſpell, dooth regenerate and make to beleeue; ſhould bee deliuered from eternall death in ſinne, and obtaine the euerlaſting glorie of God.</p>
                     <p>As I haue been ſomewhat longer in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this moſt worthie place:
<note place="margin">Direction to the gouernour of the houſe.</note> ſo I finde here a moſt large field of Catechiſme. Where I will obſerue this order, for the direction of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the houſe, (whom I perſwade my ſelfe, by that time he hath beaten the former Catechiſmes into his peoples heads, ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them better able to receiue ſtronger meate) I will ſhewe the manifeſt beautie of this ſentence, as a moſt goodly tree, where the maſter ſhall guide his folke to gather ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many kindes of fruites, to the comfortable feeding and nouriſhing of the ſoule: and how to diſcerne by the good fruite, that which is euill. Firſt therefore, the doctrines ſhall offer themſelues, out of this ſentence, with moſt
<pb facs="tcp:26366:36"/>ſweete comforts annexed vnto them: and in the ſecond place mine hand ſhall poynt out vnto him, how he may deſcrie vnto his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the errors contrary vnto the ſame. Vnto euery doctrine I will adde ſome one place of Scripture, for the further enlightning of their vnderſtanding.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrines">
                     <head>The doctrines.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">This is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed out of the whole ſway of the text, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the words, <hi>loued, gaue,</hi> and the end of giuing, which ſhewe his liuely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king towards his creatures preſeruation, &amp;c. and ſo would hee bee knowne. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. <hi>Malac.</hi> 1.2. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 9.16.</note> God is euerliuing, the moſt holy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and wiſe gouernour and Sauiour of the world.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſauing of the holie Ghoſt, which is ſhewed by the effect, <hi>beleeue,</hi> which is ſet for his cauſe, verſ. 5.1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 5.7.</note> In this one God, are three diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, God the Father, God the Sonne, &amp; God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p>Here he muſt begin to ſhewe the diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the perſons thus.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">This is in a manner expreſſed, ſauing of the holy Ghoſt, reade <hi>Ioh</hi> 15.16.</note> The Father begetteth, the Sonne begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the holy Ghoſt proceedeth from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">The beginning of the father to loue and ſend, &amp;c. the diſpenſation, it is done by the Son: the perfection, the holy Ghoſt worketh faith, &amp;c. the like, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.6.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11.</note> The beginning of euery action is giuen to the Father; the diſpenſation to the Sonne; the perfection or conſummation to the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">Made man is in the word gaue: for by incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was giuen, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1. all the reſt is clecre enough.</note> The perſon and office of Chriſt: perſon, Chriſt is the onely begotten ſonne of GOD made man: his office, he is our Sauiour.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:36"/>
6.
<note n="6" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.10.</note> The eſtate of mankinde by Adams fall is here ſhewed: for vnleſſe God had giuen his onely begotten ſonne, we had periſhed.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.
<note n="7" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph</hi> 1.5.6.7.8.9.10 and cap. 4.11.12.</note> The cauſes of our ſaluation and their concurrence and proceeding, firſt, the good pleaſure of Gods will, who freely loueth vs, the firſt cauſe: ſecondly, the matter or meanes he vſeth. Chriſt by his incarnation, ſuffering, &amp;c. thirdly, the ioyning of theſe cauſes into his forme, that is, faith apprehending Chriſt, wrought by preaching, thorow the ſpirite. Laſtly, the thing for men, euerlaſting life.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Here is taught, who are ſaued:
<note n="8" place="margin">This Chriſt ſo expoundeth in the next ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and cap. 6.40.53.</note> thoſe onely who beleeue, which is not to beleeue there is a God, or that God made the worlde, &amp;c. which yet are neceſſarie: but to beleeue in him, that is, in Ieſus Chriſt the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne of God.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Our ſaluation is moſt free &amp; certaine.
<note n="9" place="margin">It depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods loue. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Tit</hi> 1.2.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10.
<note n="10" place="margin">In the worde giue. <hi>Eph</hi> 2.8.</note> Our ſaluation is of the free grace of God, without our deſeruing.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.
<note n="11" place="margin">This is ſeen in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aboue all ſacrificers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.11.12.13.</note> Our Saluation is perfectly wrought by Chriſt alone.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.
<note n="12" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6 7.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. <hi>&amp; Mar.</hi> 16.16.</note> There are two waies of mens life, by the decree of God: ſome by beleefe in Chriſt ſhall be ſaued: ſome for vnbeleefe ſhall periſh.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. There is a double life,
<note n="13" place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> and a double death, one of the body onely, and the other of bodie and ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <pb facs="tcp:26366:37"/>
14.
<note n="14" place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15.16.</note> Here is the catholike Churche, the communion of Saintes, remiſſion of ſinnes, reſurrection of the bodie and life euerlaſting, taught. For the catholike Church is of all that beleeue in Chriſt, the communion is our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God in Chriſt, thorow the ſpirit, in the vſe of all his giftes; or there is one God, one Chriſt, one faith, and one ſaluation to all. Remiſſion of ſinnes, &amp; the reſurrection of the bodie, are part of thoſe giftes, which are ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed is this eternall life, for by forgiuenes of ſinnes, and the reſurrection of the bodie, wee come to eternall life.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.
<note n="15" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.11.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.20.</note> This place is moſt ſtrong to teache men to liue godly, ſoberly, and righteouſly in this preſent world: for what may more moue, then the free loue of God: the great price of our ſaluation the onely begotten ſonne of God; the order of our calling, by the ſpirite to be regenerate vnto faith, and laſtly the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation it ſelfe, which is to bee deliuered from ſinne?</p>
                     <p n="16">16.
<note n="16" place="margin">This is taught, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 11. <hi>cap</hi> 6 2 3. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note> You may ioyne vnto theſe, though not expreſſed in the text, as the reſt: That the Sacraments are ſignes to teach vs; as ſeales to applie vnto vs this doctrine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comforts">
                     <head>Comforts out of this doctrine.</head>
                     <p>HEre is the place to explaine the ſweete comfortes of this doctrine, which I may
<pb facs="tcp:26366:37"/>terme the pleaſant taſte of theſe good fruites: which I deſire that euery Maſter would care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and painefully drop into his familie, that they may taſte how good the Lorde is, and feele that they knowe, for this will mightelie worke towards faith: ſo that his labour ſhall be ioyfull in the ende. The comforts are gathered, by the
<list>
                           <item>conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the perſons.</item>
                           <item>meditation of the things.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comforts">
                     <head>Comforts by the conſideration of the perſons.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.32. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13.14.</note> Beholde here the great loue of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie and glorious God, the loue of Chriſt his ſonne, and of the holy Ghoſt. What was greater in God then his ſonne? That hee gaue for &amp; to vs. What is greater in the ſonne then himſelfe? That he beſtowed vpon vs. What is more precious then the power and goodnes of the ſpirit? that hee powreth into vs, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and endowing vs with faith and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. O how vnſpeakeable is the goodnes of God for the aſſurance of our ſaluation, ſo that no man can doubt, but euery ſoule that knoweth and feeleth theſe things, muſt needs reioyce with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 6.7 8.9.10. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.9.10.</note> Marke who they bee vpon whom this glorious God beſtoweth this great gift: vpon the world, euen vs men, who hauing offended
<pb facs="tcp:26366:38"/>him by ſinne are his enemies by euill mindes, and are weake, being able to doe nothing to recompenſe him, or to comfort or helpe our ſelues: but he chooſeth vs, he redeemeth vs, he ſanctifieth vs, he glorifieth vs. Muſt not this, being well wayed make vs burſt out, with the bleſſed virgin?
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.46.</note> 
                        <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lorde, and my ſpirite reioyceth in God my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comfort">
                     <head>Comfort by the meditation of the things.</head>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.2.3.4.5.6. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.10. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.3.4.5. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.12.13 <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1 5.6. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.20. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> Call to minde in what miſerie, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and wofull condition, we be of ourſelues: into what happines, freedome, and bleſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate we bee brought by Gods loue in Chriſt: from ſinne, from death, from hell, from the curſe of the lawe, from the power of Sathan, from the wrath of God and eternall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, anguiſh and ſearefull ſorrow: into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious libertie of the ſonnes of God, to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie and in corruption, to the crowne of righteouſnes, and to be the ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, heyres of the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to the fulnes of ioyes in the preſence of God for euermore. Mine heart cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, my pen cannot write the vnſearcheable riches of Chriſt: the price of this pearle, for which a man would ſell all that he hath. And this is freely giuen vs, perfectly wrought for
<pb facs="tcp:26366:38"/>vs, aſſuredly kept for vs; how may we triumph and glorie in our God? Reioyce in the Lorde alway, and againe I ſay reioyce.</p>
                     <p>When the ſoule is thus ſeaſoned with the taſte of this heauenly doctrine,
<note place="margin">Admonition to the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder.</note> then may the Maſter of the familie boldlie deſcrie vnto them, the errors which are contrarie to theſe trueths. And this he ſhall finde a perfect rule: that the true doctrine being once vprightly taught; whatſoeuer is not agreeing thereunto, is falſehood and to be auoyded: as
<note n="a" place="margin">Epiſt. 2. ver. 9</note> Iohn tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, <hi>Whoſoeuer tranſgreſſeth, and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God.</hi> Now the errors are infinite, as there are many by-waies, and but one true waie: <hi>So
<note n="b" place="margin">
                              <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.31.</note> God made man righteous, but they haue found out many inuentions.</hi> I will name but a fewe in compariſon, yet ſo many as I would the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe, ſhould vſe diſcretion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing of them to his familie, namely ſome fewe at once: and ſo it wil much further them; euen as by all contraries, euery good thing is the more perceiued, felt and eſteemed. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating of theſe, he muſt rehearſe the true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and ſo compare them together, that they may perceiue this to bee contrary to that: as light vnto darknes. And therefore by figures, anſwering to the doctrines, I wil ſhew him, which are contrarie to each other, and
<pb facs="tcp:26366:39"/>with a little heede taking and attention hee ſhall finde it eaſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="errors">
                     <head>The errors and hereſies contrarie to the good doctrine.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. THe firſt doctrine condemneth all theſe, <hi>i.</hi> the Atheiſts of whom Pſal. 14.1. Secondly, the Philoſophers who make God, to bee idle, and not to haue care of the world: thirdly, the gentiles, who turned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of the incorruptible God, into the image of a corruptible man, and of birdes, &amp;c. Rom. 1.23. Fourthly, they
<note n="c" place="margin">Saturnians.</note> who make one God of the Iewes, and another of the gentiles, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrarie to other, reade Rom. 3.29. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note n="a" place="margin">Symonians.</note> they who affirme, that the diuell hath free power ouer all thinges, Iob. 1.8.9. Sixtly, ſome aſcribe ouermuch to phificke, pollicie ſtrength and witches, reade 1. Sam. 2.3.8.9. Pſal. 36.6. Prou. 21.30.31. Seuenthly,
<note n="b" place="margin">Priſcillia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</note> ſome make ſtarres and planets to gouerne mens actions, Hier. 10.1. Eyghtly, ſome aſcribe the euent of things to fortune, ſome the being and continuance of thinges to nature, reade Eſay. 45.5, 6, 7. Rom. 11.36. Reuel. 4.11.</p>
                     <p n="2 3 4">2.3.4. To theſe three of the Trinitie, are contrarie, three heretikes: firſt,
<note n="c" place="margin">Montaniſts.</note> who ſay there is but one perſon in the trinity, which is called
<pb facs="tcp:26366:39"/>by diuers names, of father, ſonne, and holy Ghoſt. Secondly,
<note n="d" place="margin">Aetians.</note> who ſaye the three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to bee onely three qualities: Thirdly,
<note n="e" place="margin">Triformians.</note> who affirme the three perſons to bee three diuers and ſeparable Gods, 1. Corinth. 8.4. 1. Iohn 5.7.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, againſt the perſon of Chriſt, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell hath fought by many heretikes. Some
<note n="f" place="margin">Neſtorians,</note> make one perſon of his diuinitie, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his humanitie: ſome
<note n="g" place="margin">Arrians.</note> make Chriſt to be God, not by nature but by grace, and to be leſſe then his father. Some
<note n="h" place="margin">Bonoſians.</note> call Chriſt an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted ſonne, ſome
<note n="i" place="margin">Marcellians.</note> ſay he was not begotten of the father: ſome
<note n="k" place="margin">Carpocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</note> ſay Chriſt was conceiued after the manner of other men.
<note n="l" place="margin">Apollinaris.</note> Some will haue his bodie to bee heauenly, and not of the Virgin Marie.
<note n="m" place="margin">Eunomians.</note> Some denie Chriſt a minde.
<note n="n" place="margin">Eutyches.</note> Some auouch the humane nature to bee ſwallowed vp of the diuine.
<note n="o" place="margin">Timotheans.</note> Some confound the two natures of Chriſt, and make him a mixt third thing.</p>
                     <p>The doctrine of the office of Chriſt doth condemne the Symonians, Sethians, Menan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all that ſhew any other ſauiour or meanes of ſaluation or additament, more then Chriſt onely and the faith and doctrine of him. Such as are the Papiſts, who ioyne mans workes, merits, ſatisfactions, pardons, pilgrimages, prayers, purgatorie, and I cannot tell what trumperie, as additaments to Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:40"/>Acts 4.11. Iohn 10.1, 2, 3. and 14.6. Gal. 6.14.15. Reuel. 22.18. ſome
<note n="a" place="margin">Manichies.</note> ſay the ſoule one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſaued, and
<note n="b" place="margin">Paternians.</note> ſome the vpper partes of the bodie, Rom. 8.1. Philip. 3.21.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The doctrine of the eſtate of man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, condemneth them
<note n="c" place="margin">Pelagians.</note> who deny children to be corrupted with originall ſinne, and that without the grace of God a man may doe all the commandements of God, and
<note n="d" place="margin">Papiſts.</note> they who dreame of certaine pure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals, by which they imagine they can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues to grace, and worke with grace the merit to ſaluation, 2. Cor. 3.5. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. 2.13. Heb. 12.2. There bee alſo ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, who thorow ignorance, doe very lightly feele their miſerie, and how wickedly ſoeuer they liue, they yet fancie to themſelues an happie eſtate, they ſay they will doe well, or pray, or aske pardon: but not feeling the deep wound of ſinne, they little feare the ſore and grieuous puniſhment which hangeth ouer their heads, for neglecting ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by Chriſt. Heb. 2.1.2.3. and 12.25.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. The doctrine of the cauſes of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion firſt in the good pleaſure of Gods will condemneth them,
<note n="e" place="margin">Pelagians.</note> who doe vtterly deny predeſtination to eſtabliſh free-will. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <note n="f" place="margin">Papists.</note> who tye it to workes foreſeene. Rom. 9.11. Concerning Chriſt, the meanes, it condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them
<note n="g" place="margin">Heracleans.</note> who put in his roome oyntments
<pb facs="tcp:26366:40"/>and ceremonies. And the Papiſts as before in the 5. Heb. 1.5. The doctrine of faith apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, is againſt the Papiſts, who would ioyne workes. Rom. 3.28.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. This ouerthroweth all Atheiſts, Deiſts, Sophiſters, and ignorant brablers, who frame to themſelues a God, or ſaluation, without faith in Chriſt. 1. Tim. 3.16. Gal. 3.26.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. The doctrine of certaintie, confuteth the Papiſts, who would haue men to doubt of their ſaluation. Heb. 10.19.20.21.23.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Free ſaluation excludeth merit. Tit. 3.4.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Perfect ſaluation ouerthroweth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, and much popiſh traſh. 2. Pet. 1.3.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. This ouerthroweth Purgatorie, which is made a third place, contrarie to 1. Iohn. 1.7.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. This refelleth them,
<note n="a" place="margin">Cerdonians.</note> who deny the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or
<note n="b" place="margin">Hymineus &amp; Philetus.</note> ſay it is paſt alreadie, or
<note n="c" place="margin">Epicures.</note> make their happines in this life. 1. Theſſ. 4.14. 1. Ioh. 3.1.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. This reprooueth them,
<note n="d" place="margin">Gnoſtici.</note> who make faith a naked knowledge of the Goſpel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fruites of good workes: or
<note n="e" place="margin">Libertines.</note> make good workes contrarie to faith, or
<note n="f" place="margin">Antitactae.</note> will men to be free from Gods commandements Eph. 4.24. Gal. 5.6. Eph. 2.10.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Concerning the Sacraments in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, onely here if it can bee taught, the difference of the outward ſigne and the thing
<pb facs="tcp:26366:41"/>ſignified, and that theſe are not to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, neither that which is proper to the one, to bee giuen to the other; it ſhall giue cleere ſight againſt many errors. As
<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.31.</note> Peter ſpeaketh of Baptiſme, that it ſaueth vs, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his meaning, ſaying, not the waſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the filth of the fleſh, which is the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne: but the inward working of the ſpirit, which is in the anſwer to God, and by the reſurrection of Chriſt. So
<note n="h" place="margin">22.19.</note> Chriſt calling the bread his bodie, dooth yet teach vs to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this rule; when he biddeth vs doe all that actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of receiuing it, <hi>in remembrance of him.</hi> So that the outward action is as the ſigne and ſeale, but the power of working is in the thing ſignified, which is Chriſt by his ſpirit, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through faith, that heauenly waſhing, and foode vnto our ſoules.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 9. <hi>The ſeuenth Catechiſme, for establiſhing of iudgement.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEre I will chooſe two places of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe mine eſpeciall purpoſe is to teach the doctrine of the Sacraments, and handle them both together: and becauſe they are ſeales of the couenant of grace, the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant alſo is therewithall to be declared, that the one may ſhewe the vſe of the other, and
<pb facs="tcp:26366:41"/>each take light &amp; ſtrength from other: which I can hardly doe out of any one text.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="text">
                     <head>The firſt Text.</head>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Tit. 3. verſ. 3.</hi>
                           </bibl> We our ſelues were in times paſt vnwiſe, diſobedient, deceiued, ſeruing the luſts &amp; diuers pleaſures, liuing in maliciouſnes and enuie, hatefull, and hating one another.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>4.</hi>
                           </bibl> But when the bountifulnes and loue of God our Sauiour, towards man appeared:</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>5.</hi>
                           </bibl> Not by the works of righteouſnes, which wee had done, but according to his mercie hee ſaued vs, by the waſhing of the new birth, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>6.</hi>
                           </bibl> Which he ſhed on vs abundantly through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>7.</hi>
                           </bibl> That wee being iustified by his grace, ſhould bee made heires according to hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</p>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="text">
                     <head>The ſecond Text.</head>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>1. Cor. 11.23.</hi>
                           </bibl> I haue receiued of the Lord, that which I alſo haue deliuered vnto you, that the Lord Ieſus the ſame night hee was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied, tooke bread:</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Verſ. 24.</hi>
                           </bibl> And when he had giuen thanks he brake it and ſayd, Take, eate, this is my bodie, which is broken for you, doe this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>25.</hi>
                           </bibl> After the ſame manner alſo hee tooke
<pb facs="tcp:26366:42"/>the cup when he had ſupped, ſaying, This cup is the new Testament in my bloud, doe this as oft as you drinke it in remembrance of me.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>26.</hi>
                           </bibl> For as oft as you eate this bread, or drinke this cuppe, ye ſhew the Lords death till he come.</p>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The Interpretation.</head>
                     <p>THeſe two places haue one end,
<note place="margin">Both texts to one end.</note> namely, to teach good order and good behauiour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Gods people: the firſt touching all dueties, and the latter in the ſeruice of God, as namely in the vſe of the Sacraments.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is by a compariſon of the eſtate of Chriſtians before their calling,
<note place="margin">The firſt text.</note> with that wherein they are after they be called: the
<note n="a" place="margin">Were in times paſt. verſ. 3.</note> firſt eſtate is verſe 3. in theſe wordes, <hi>were in time past:</hi> where he deſcribeth the nature of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate, in the
<note n="b" place="margin">Wee our ſelues.</note> perſon of the Chriſtian in theſe words, <hi>we our ſelues,</hi> firſt the corruption of the
<note n="c" place="margin">Vnwiſe, Diſobedient, Deceiued.</note> 
                        <hi>minde, vnwiſe</hi> in the vnderſtanding part, <hi>diſobedient in will, and deceiued in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Secondly, in the
<note n="d" place="margin">Seruing the luſts &amp; diuers pleaſures.</note> affections, <hi>ſeruing the luſts and pleaſures.</hi> Thirdly, in
<note n="e" place="margin">Liuing in maliciouſnes and enuie.</note> conuerſation, liuing in all wickednes to the hurt of others: and this is ſet forth by the
<note n="f" place="margin">Hatefull and hating. verſ. 4.</note> effect, <hi>that one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the other.</hi> By which hee emptieth man of all righteouſnes, and ſtrippeth him naked, that he may bee ſeene, to be nothing but filthines. Then the other eſtate is ſhewed in the reſt.
<pb facs="tcp:26366:42"/>Firſt, by the
<note n="g" place="margin">Bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of God.</note> fundamentall cauſe, <hi>the ſecret bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes &amp; loue of God.</hi> And becauſe God is
<note n="h" place="margin">Our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</note> author of chriſtian happines wholy &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is intituled <hi>Our Sauiour,</hi> this bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is ſet forth, by the
<note n="i" place="margin">When appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. verſ. 5.</note> time when it was knowne and effectuall, <hi>when it appeared</hi> and this is verſe 4. Then verſe 5. he ſheweth
<note n="k" place="margin">According to his mercie.</note> how it is wrought, namely by mercie, that is, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on our infirmities and miſeries, being ſuch deſperate ſinners, which is opened by his
<note n="a" place="margin">Not by the works of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes which we had done.</note> contrarie, that it was not by <hi>our workes of righteouſnes.</hi> Then hee ſheweth
<note n="b" place="margin">He ſaued vs.</note> what God did, <hi>he ſaued vs,</hi> namely from that miſerable eſtate of ſinne: and this is declared by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, which is double, one
<note n="c" place="margin">Waſhing.</note> outward of leſſe power, which is <hi>waſhing,</hi> that is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: the other
<note n="d" place="margin">Holy ghoſt.</note> inward which is effectuall, and maketh the waſhing effectuall, this is the holy <hi>Spirite:</hi> and that by two
<note n="e" place="margin">New birth and renewing.</note> effectes, the new birth or regeneration vnto faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of vs in ſanctification vnto holynes. And verſe 6.
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ </seg>6</label> theſe two effects are ſet forth by the holy
<note n="f" place="margin">Ieſus Chriſt.</note> conduit or meanes, by which they are powred downe vpon vs, which is aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly by Chriſt: and then verſe 7.
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ </seg>7</label> by the
<note n="g" place="margin">Iuſtified and made heires, &amp;c.</note> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, <hi>that we ſhould be iuſtified by his grace,</hi> (that is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.</note> freely reconciled vnto God by faith in Chriſts blood) <hi>and made heyres of eternall life.</hi> This latter effect is declared by his
<note n="h" place="margin">Hope.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, <hi>Hope.</hi> The ſumme is then, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:26366:43"/>by nature wee are ſo corrupt in minde, in will, affections and workes, and that God of his bountifulnes without our workes, moued onely by his mercie, hath begotten vs a new, and ſanctified vs with his ſpirit, whereof Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a Sacrament, &amp; all this by Chriſt, &amp;c. We ought to bee ſubject to principalities and powers, obedient and readie to euerie good worke.</p>
                     <p>The other place,
<note place="margin">The ſecond text opened.</note> is by a rehearſall of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, that by it as by a rule or lawe, the Corinthian abuſes and diſorders might be reformed, where firſ is the
<note n="i" place="margin">I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord, &amp;c.</note> preface to make it a rule, becauſe he deliuerad to them that he receiued from the Lorde: inſinuating that hee durſt not teach them any thing elſe, and therefore they did ill to corrupt that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by their abuſes: then for the thing it ſelfe, he firſt ſimplie and truly ſheweth the very ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and after he expoundeth the vſe of it. In the ſtorie he beginneth with the
<note n="a" place="margin">The night he was betrayed.</note> time that it was ordayned, <hi>The ſame night he was betrayed:</hi> namely the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.16.17 <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.2.9.</note> time of the olde teſtament in the ſhadowes, hauing in him an ende, he erecteth ordinances for the new: then ſecondly hee ſheweth the
<note n="b" place="margin">Hee tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>read and brake, &amp;c. verſ. 24.</note> things. Firſt, that hee tooke <hi>bread,</hi> then that hee bleſſed it by
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note> giuing thankes, that is, hee ſeparated it to ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vſe, to that end followeth the breaking the bread, and bidding them to take and eate it:
<pb facs="tcp:26366:43"/>then he ſheweth the
<note n="c" place="margin">This is my bodie.</note> vſe of theſe ceremonies in theſe words: <hi>this is my bodie,</hi> which is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally ſpoken (as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.11.12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3.4.</note> that of the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and of Manna, and the rocke, &amp;c.) that that breaking of bread was a ſigne of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be broken, which he expoundeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the
<note n="d" place="margin">This doe ye in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of me.</note> next wordes: which are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by vertue whereof, the Churche ought to vſe this Sacrament, namely, that the Church ſhould doe as hee did, and when they ſo doe, they ſhould doe it in remembrance of him. Then verſe 25.
<label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>25</label> hee ſheweth the
<note n="e" place="margin">After the ſame manner, &amp;c.</note> like of the cup, where the words of the
<note n="f" place="margin">This cuppe is the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, &amp;c.</note> vſe, are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a borrowed ſpeech, the cuppe for the wine in the cup: and alluding to the
<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.8.</note> righte of the ſacrifices, he calleth it the teſtament in his blood: meaning that it was a ſacramentall ſigne of the couenant of God, ſealed with his blood: which leaſt we ſhould dreame of any Tranſubſtantiation, or conſubſtantiation, hee likewiſe expoundeth himſelfe, in a
<note n="h" place="margin">This doe as oft as ye, &amp;c.</note> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the Church, that when they drinke it, they ſhould doe as he did in remembrance of him. Now the Apoſtle hauing the ſame ſpirit of Chriſt, in that very meaning doth teach vs the
<note n="i" place="margin">As oft as ye. &amp;c. verſ. 26.</note> vſe, verſe 26. calling the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in the eating <hi>bread;</hi> and in the drinking <hi>wine:</hi> and that the ſame bread and wine, ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by thankeſgiuing, are not changed in their ſubſtance, but in their vſe, namely that it
<pb facs="tcp:26366:44"/>is not now as common bread to feede our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies onely, but it hath a ſacramentall and holy vſe annexed, for the feeding of our ſoules, that is, <hi>Wee ſhew the Lordes death herein till hee come.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſumme then is: ſeeing hee deliuered vnto them, onely that he receiued, and that in this order and to this vſe: they muſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane this holy Sacrament, by their diſorder or additaments what ſo euer to doe in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order, or to any other vſe, more or leſſe, then it was ordained. Whereupon he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the reſt of the chapter, to giue them certain canons or precepts, out of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: namely, how they ſhould reforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and doe it orderly and profitablie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="doctrine">
                     <head>The Doctrine of the Catechiſme.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Out of both places.</note> Theſe two places open vnto vs the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God, touching the ſaluation of his elect, by two things. Firſt, by doctrine as a writing declaratorie. Secondly, by Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as ſeales of that writing, confirmatory.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The doctrine is in the deſcription of the perſons, couenanting one with another, and the couenant it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">In the firſt place, verſ. 4.5.6.</note> The firſt perſon is he who offereth the couenant, namely God: who is deſcribed, by the ſpeciall worke which hee doth in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, hee maketh his bountifulnes appeare,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:44"/>and is therefore intituled a Sauiour, as one that ſeeketh vs, and not we him.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The ſecond, man,
<note n="4" place="margin">Verſ. 3. ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out pure naturals, free will, &amp;c.</note> who receiueth the couenants, who is deſcribed voyde of all goodnes, in minde, will, affections, &amp; works: for ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.4.5.8.</note> God findeth vs in our filthines before the couenant.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place. verſ. 24.25.</note> The third perſon is the mediator of the couenant, <hi>Chriſt:</hi> who giueth his body and blood for the confirmation of the couenant.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.
<note n="6" place="margin">This is out of both places.</note> The couenant it ſelfe is firſt called the new Teſtament, that is,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31.31.</note> not of the lawe of workes, but of mercie and grace. Therefore on the partie that offereth it is thus deſcribed. Firſt, God propoundeth himſelfe to bee our God and Sauiour: then hee receiueth vs to himſelfe by mercie in Chriſt, and not by our workes. Thirdly, he ſheweth the effect of the couenant, that wee ſhould bee iuſtified by his grace, and made heyres thorow hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life. On our part the condition is no more, but to receiue all this by faith in Chriſt, which is giuen vs in the new birth, and therefore
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſpirite of Adoption, by which wee call God, <hi>Father.</hi> And ſo the couenant is made on our part, as it is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.</note> written, <hi>Yee are all the ſonnes of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Where you may ſee that Chriſt is the mediator
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18.</note> to bring vs to God, namely, by beleefe in him. Which couenant God will haue declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:26366:45"/>men, by the vſe of his ſeruice, as profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sacraments, &amp;c. and by obedience vnto euery good worke.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. In beholding which couenant, wee may ſee all merit and reioycing in man, vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded. For before the couenant, wee are altogether voyde of all goodnes: in the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wee are receiued and ſaued by mercie without workes: Chriſt is a mediator to God for vs, paying the ranſome of our ſinnes: by him is powred vpon vs the new birth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the holy Ghoſt: by him we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, and made heyres of euerlaſting life. If we haue faith or hope, they are all the giftes of God thorow Chriſt: ſo that wee haue euery way, cauſe of abaſing our ſelues, and onely to
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> reioyce in him. Wherefore the Church aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing nothing to her ſelfe, maketh this ioyfull confeſſion.
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay.</hi> 61.10.</note> 
                        <hi>I will greatly reioyce in the Lord, and my ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God: for he hath clothed mee with the garments of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and couered me with the robe of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now not minding to ſhew euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar poynt which theſe two places affoord,
<note place="margin">An obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> we will come to the ſecond parte of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. In handling whereof, if any thing bee not in one of theſe two texts (for it were much all to be) I will ſet in the margine ſome other place, as a ſupplie to their wants: and this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb facs="tcp:26366:45"/>is in two things. 1. How many Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 2. What they be.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. There are but two Sacraments of the
<note n="*" place="margin">I ſay couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, becauſe the word ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is vſed diuerſly: this ſhutteth of vnproper vſes.</note> couenant, that is to ſay, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
                     <p>The other poynt, <hi>What they bee,</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare eaſie, if wee learne how they agree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, and how they differ both betweene themſelues, and alſo from others.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">Two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments agree in foure things.</note> Theſe two Sacraments agree in theſe things. 1. In a generall definition: <hi>A Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a ſigne and ſeale of the couenant of grace.</hi> Firſt, they are ſignes,
<note n="1" place="margin">In a generall definition.</note> as water &amp; waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Baptiſme; bread and wine, eating and drinking in the Lords Supper. They are both ſignes of the couenant: for Baptiſme ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Chriſts bloud in the couenant, and ſo dooth the Lords Supper: and they bee both more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bare ſignes, euen ſeales of aſſurance. For as the ſeale is ſet to a will or deed, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the writing: ſo are theſe two appointed by Chriſt, to aſſure vs of the thing they ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. Therefore the one is called his body, and the other the waſhing of the new birth: not becauſe they bee chaunged in nature, but by ſuch a neere ſpeech to aſſure vs of the thing ſealed or ſigned. They both herein aſſure vs of our iuſtification and ſanctification. Secondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">They be as badges.</note> they bee both outward badges of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as by the one we ſhew the Lords death,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:46"/>and by the other that wee are Gods children by a new birth. Thirdly,
<note n="3" place="margin">Both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.</note> they both haue a commandement from Chriſt. Fourthly,
<note n="4" place="margin">Both haue a forme of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.14.37.38. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.16</note> they both haue a preſcribed forme of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in regard of the Miniſter and people. The Miniſter is appoynted to preach and declare the couenant, and to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the people to heare and to receiue the Sacraments. In Baptiſme the Miniſter muſt waſh with water, in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt: the perſon to bee admitted into the Church, is to ſubmit himſelfe to ſuch a waſhing. In the Lords Supper, the Miniſter by thankſgiuing is to ſet apart, to this holy vſe, the bread &amp; wine ſeuerally, to breake the bread, and to giue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſeuerally, firſt bread, and then wine, to the people, bidding them to eate &amp; drinke, &amp;c. and the people ought to receiue them both ſeuerally, firſt bread, and then wine, and to eate the bread and drinke the wine: not as common bread and wine, but as ſanctified to the holy vſe by Chriſt preſcribed.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.
<note n="10" place="margin">The firſt diſagreement with others.</note> The fiue forged Sacraments of the Church of Rome, cannot bee reckoned with theſe; becauſe they are not pertaining to the couenant, nor commaunded by God, with outward ſignes to the vſes here deſcribed: but either haue no outward ſignes, as Penance: or els other ſignifications and vſes: As Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie
<pb facs="tcp:26366:46"/>hath no ſigne ordained of God to this vſe, but ſometime is made an
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hoſeah.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.</note> allegorie, or metaphor, and ſometime is taught by compariſon, from Chriſt and his Church. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue impoſition of hands, but not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God for the grace of this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or to bee badges of our profeſsion, but for the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> grace of the office of the Miniſtrie. So the annoynting of the ſicke in the Goſpell is not taught, as the Papiſts vſe it: but only to bee an
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.14.</note> outward ſigne, in healing the bodie: but a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is for the comfort of the ſoule. The like may be ſayd of the other.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.
<note n="11" place="margin">The ſecond difference in themſelues.</note> The differences betweene theſe two Sacraments of the couenant in themſelues, are theſe. 1. In the ſigne, Baptiſme hath wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and waſhing: the Lords Supper hath bread and wine, eating and drinking, &amp;c. 2. In the manner of ſignifying; becauſe they apply the couenant to vs in diuers ſorts. Baptiſme ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth it, as our firſt entring into couenant, and there it ſignifieth our new birth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing, &amp;c. and therefore all that are
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47. with the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> firſt receiued into the Church are admitted by Baptiſme; and a man is but once baptized, becauſe hee is but once to bee borne againe. The Lords Supper applieth the couenant, in regard of the euerlaſting continuance of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour betweene God and vs in Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee eate bread and drinke wine, as liuely
<pb facs="tcp:26366:47"/>ſignes of our growing &amp; increaſing in Chriſt, in faith and good life, and in all aſſurednes of eternall life: And therefore it is often vſed, that wee may continually bee ſtrengthened and confirmed in his grace, from faith to faith.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.
<note n="12" place="margin">The third difference from others.</note> In all this declaration, agreeing to holie Scripture, and ſo in all the Bible beſide, you ſhall neuer ſinde that the Sacraments by the outward worke wrought, doe giue grace: or that the ſigne leeſeth his nature to be turned into the thing ſignified: or that there is a reall, locall and corporall preſence of the thing, in the outward ſigne: or that in Baptiſme, exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme, creame, ſpettle, ſalt, or any other thing is to be mingled, or vſed, but onely water: or that in the Lords Supper there ſhould bee an vnbloudie ſacrifice, the bread adored, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or carried about, or the wine ſhould bee kept from the common people. Therefore all theſe, and whatſoeuer other additaments and abuſes of the holy Sacraments, are altogether to be reiected and condemned, by the rule A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall, becauſe they are not receiued of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>Here the maſter of the familie may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the ſubſtance of the former Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme to his folke, by this place.</p>
                     <p>1. Cor. 12. verſ. 13. <hi>By one ſpirit wee are all
<pb facs="tcp:26366:47"/>baptized into one bodie, whether we bee Iewes or Grecians, whether we bee bond or free, and haue been all made to drinke into one ſpirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">One bodie, one ſpirit.</note> Where one bodie and one ſpirit to Iew and Gentill, &amp;c. ſhew the couenant in grace and communion of God with all nations and ſorts of people thorow Chriſt, by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in one bodie.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Both Sacraments teach,
<note place="margin">Baptiſed into. Drinke into.</note> there is one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie communion betweene GOD and his Church.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Baptiſme, our regeneration and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration into the ſame communion: the Lords Supper, our daily nouriſhment from our head Chriſt, growing together in the ſame couenant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 10. <hi>The fourth order of Catechiſme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOw for the maſters further helpe,
<note place="margin">To the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder.</note> I will commend vnto him theſe foure places: namely, Epheſ. 2.8.9.10. 2. Theſſ. 2.13.14. Tit. 2.11.12.13.14. Iam. 1.18. whereof hee ſhall ſee euery one fit to bring into his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the doctrines of the former Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes. And I hope both he and his familie, may eaſily gather the ſame of themſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ripe thereunto by their former pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe:
<pb facs="tcp:26366:48"/>reioycing in the plentifull and ſweete conſent of ſo many places of Gods word, and admiring the goodnes of God, that ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly and liberally beſtoweth vpon vs his rich treaſures of wiſedom and vnderſtanding. And if in them he finde ſomething not eaſie, let the maſter repayre to his paſtor, and ſeeke the lawe at his mouth: <hi>For
<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Malac.</hi> 2.7.</note> his lippes ſhould preſerue knowledge, being the meſſenger of the Lorde of hostes: and
<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> 4.1.</note> ſteward of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of GOD.</hi> Howbeit, in ſo waightie and needfull prouiſion, I woulde haue this houſholder to bee well ſtored, that hee maye feede his familie with more ioy and plentie, to make them ſtrong &amp; well liking in the houſe of our God, children, that boldly will anſwer the enemie in the gates, and ſight valiantly the battels of the Lord. Therefore I will here adde two Catechiſmes more for his helpe: where the firſt will ſhew him in a notable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Iacobs Ladder: namely, by what ſteppes God bringeth all his children into the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the heauenly manſions of his diuine palace. And this is in one ſcripture moſt orderly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact together, by the heauenly ſpirit. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is
<note n="*" place="margin">Therefore I make it a book by itſelfe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uide it into chapters.</note> a more perfect bodie of Chriſtirn doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, of many and diuers places of ſcripture: as a ſhining light vnto the feete of all Gods
<pb facs="tcp:26366:48"/>children, in the dayes of their pilgrimage, till they ſhal come into the land of their cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall inheritance.</p>
                  <div type="catechism">
                     <head>The eyght Catechiſme for helpe of the houſholder.</head>
                     <head type="sub">The text.</head>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Epheſ. 1.3.</hi>
                           </bibl> Bleſſed bee God, euen the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: which hath bleſſed vs with all ſpirituall bleſſings, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things in Christ.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>4.</hi>
                           </bibl> As hee hath choſen vs, in him, before the foundation of the world: that wee ſhould bee holie and without blame before him in loue.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>5.</hi>
                           </bibl> Who hath predeſtinated vs, to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted thorow Ieſus Chriſt, vnto himſelfe: according to the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>6.</hi>
                           </bibl> To the praiſe of the glorie of his grace, wherewith hee hath made vs accepted in his beloued.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>7.</hi>
                           </bibl> By whom we haue redemption through his blood: euen the forgiuenes of ſinnes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his rich grace.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>8.</hi>
                           </bibl> Whereby hee hath been aboundant to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, in all wiſdome and vnderstanding.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>9.</hi>
                           </bibl> And opened vnto vs the mysterie of his will, according to the good pleaſure, which he had purpoſed in him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:26366:49"/>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>10.</hi>
                           </bibl> That in the dispenſation of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of times; he might gather together in one, all thinges, both which are in heauen, and which are in earth.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>In ſhewing the Catechiſme out of this text, I will follow this order. In the middle, by interpretation I will poynte out the golden ſteppes of this heauenly
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12.</note> ladder, by which the elect doe walke vp into heauen: and in the margin the particular poyntes of doctrine, as the goodly
<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 10.18.</note> Lions on both ſide of the ſteps of Salomons throne, which with little marking, thou maiſt perceiue to offer themſelues,
<note place="margin">The poynts of doctrine.</note> in the meaning of the words.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="interpretation">
                     <head>The interpretation or ladder.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. HEre is the top of Salomons throne: for hee ſheweth in this verſe, the ſtate of all faithfull Chriſtians in this life, after their effectuall calling: that they haue, as it were, liuery and ſeſin of that heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Where the bleſſing is that of Abraham Gen. 22. communicated vnto them by the
<note n="a" place="margin">The trinitie.</note> ſpirite: and it is deſcribed by the author
<note n="a" place="margin">The trinitie.</note> 
                        <hi>God the
<note n="b" place="margin">Chriſt in his perſon, Gods ſonne, in office Lord Ieſus &amp; Chriſt. i an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, king, prieſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</note> Father, of our
<note n="a" place="margin">The trinitie.</note> Lorde Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> and by the nature of it, which is <hi>heauenly,</hi> which may be tranſlated, as chap. 2.6. <hi>heauenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> becauſe the
<note n="c" place="margin">The ſtate of beleeuers: to bee heires of heauen.</note> bleſſing is to make vs heyres of heauen by hope, as is expounded verſe 13.14. and Titus. 3.7. and it is ſet forth by the
<pb facs="tcp:26366:49"/>meanes which is
<note n="a" place="margin">Chriſt the meanes.</note> Chriſt, namely, that being in Chriſt, we haue this bleſſing, Gal. 3.14. and it is ſaide, all ſpirituall bleſſings, becauſe
<note n="b" place="margin">The Spirit the worker.</note> by the ſpirite all giftes neceſſarie to eternall life, are giuen vs, 1. Pet. 1.3. and he teacheth them to prayſe
<note n="c" place="margin">God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note> God as the author, ſaying. <hi>Bleſſed be God, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hauing ſhewed that the faithfull, are ſet by Chriſt, thorow the ſpirit, in the ſtate of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it were tranſlated from death to life: now in the reſt hee ſheweth the proceeding of the cauſes, as the ſteppes by which GOD bringeth vs vnto this, and ſo in the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of all the elect, vnto the perfection of ioye, in the life to come.</p>
                     <p>Verſe 4. He ſheweth the firſt ſteppe:
<note n="d" place="margin">The firſt cauſe of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, choſen before the world was.</note> God doth chuſe them: this is declared by the time, that is, before all time: and by the
<note n="e" place="margin">God in cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing looked not on worke or faith fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene, but on his ſonne.</note> mouing cauſe in Chriſt, &amp; by the
<note n="f" place="margin">Godly life an effect, not a cauſe of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> end, that we ſhould be holy, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Verſe 5. He ſheweth here a ſecond cauſe or degree; which is,
<note n="g" place="margin">The ſecond cauſe of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, adoption thorow Chriſt</note> 
                        <hi>Adoption,</hi> that is, God would take vs to bee his children, which is ſet forth, by the repetition of the firſt cauſe,
<note n="h" place="margin">They that are adopted, were firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated.</note> predeſtination, which is generall to electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reprobation, namely, that out of it came adoption, that is, God ſet downe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, whom he would make his children tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Chriſt, which is called the ſure foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, 2. Tim. 2.19. and this illuſtrated by
<pb facs="tcp:26366:50"/>another
<note n="i" place="margin">The good pleaſure of Gods will, the mouing cauſe of predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> mouing cauſe, which is the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
                     <p>Verſe. 6. The former cauſe is here ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the laſt
<note n="k" place="margin">The glory of God the finall cauſe.</note> final: <hi>the glorie of Gods grace.</hi> Which
<note n="l" place="margin">The grace of God a third cauſe.</note> grace is made a third and ſpeciall working cauſe, bringing forth a fourth, which is our
<note n="m" place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a fourth cauſe.</note> iuſtification, for hee ſaith that with
<note n="n" place="margin">If it bee of grace, it is not now of works. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6.</note> grace he maketh them accepted; and to bee accepted, is alone with iuſtified, and his grace being the cauſe thereof, ſheweth that wee are freely iuſtified by his grace, Rom. 3.24. And laſtly, that we may know this iuſtifying to be
<note n="o" place="margin">We are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by grace thorow faith in Chriſt.</note> by faith in Chriſt, he addeth <hi>him,</hi> as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall cauſe in all theſe cauſes, terming him beloued, by excellencie, becauſe for his ſake God doth theſe things.</p>
                     <p>Verſe 7. The
<note n="a" place="margin">Redemption by Chriſts bloud, a fift cauſe.</note> fift cauſe of our ſaluation is redemption by Chriſts blood, &amp; this is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the
<note n="b" place="margin">Forgiuenes of ſinnes, part of redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. His bloud ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth Chriſt a naturall man.</note> effect, forgiuenes of ſinnes, which ſheweth how Chriſt is the meanes of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, namely in that hee payed the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for our ſinnes: and ſo wee being forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, are accounted iuſt for his ſake, as is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 2. Cor. 5.17.20.21. which is amplified by repetition of the working cauſe, his grace:
<note n="c" place="margin">Rich is the grace of God in forgiuenes of ſinnes.</note> which for the exceeding greatnes is called rich.</p>
                     <p>Verſe 8.9. Here he ſheweth a
<note n="d" place="margin">The preaching of the Goſpell, a ſixt cauſe.</note> ſixt cauſe, euen the inſtrument, by which he applieth all
<pb facs="tcp:26366:50"/>theſe cauſes vnto vs: which is the preaching of the Goſpell called here,
<note n="e" place="margin">The Goſpell is the opening of the miſtery of Gods will, in all wiſdome and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> 
                        <hi>The opening of the mystery of his will:</hi> So expounded, cap. 3.4, 5, 6. Coloſſ. 1.25.26. Which thing is ſet forth, firſt, by the cauſe: <hi>whereby,</hi> that is his grace: ſecondly, by the order of it, that it was aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in all wiſdome and vnderſtanding: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the
<note n="f" place="margin">The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, commeth of Gods grace and good pleaſure.</note> repetition of one mouing cauſe, <hi>The good pleaſure of his will:</hi> and laſtly, by the firſt cauſe, his
<note n="g" place="margin">Preaching of the goſpell, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of Gods purpoſe.</note> purpoſe: wherein he regarded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Chriſt, wherefore hee ſaith in him: that is, as God purpoſed in his good pleaſure to elect and adopt theſe happie ſoules in Chriſt: ſo did he in that purpoſe appoynt the meanes; which is the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</p>
                     <p>Verſe 10. The
<note n="h" place="margin">Our effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all calling, the ſeuenth cauſe.</note> laſt cauſe, which is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall calling, named the
<note n="i" place="margin">All the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gathered into one.</note> gathering into one. The greeke word ſignifieth the gathering of diſperſed things, into one entire or ſumme, namely, that where we be in all ages, as ſheep going aſtray, we are called by the goſpell, and gathered by fayth vnto Chriſt our ſhepheard; into one felowſhip or bodie: which then ſhall be
<note n="k" place="margin">There is a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, which ſhall be made full vp in Chriſt.</note> perfected, when the whole number of the elect, being accompliſhed, we ſhall all meete with Chriſt, and hee made meruellous in all that beleeue, Epheſ. 4.12, 13. which calling is ſet forth by two argumentes. Firſt, by the times, wherein there is a
<note n="a" place="margin">The faithfull called in all times &amp; ages.</note> diſpenſation of
<pb facs="tcp:26366:51"/>times, and a
<note n="b" place="margin">In the end of time all the elect ſhall be one with Chriſt.</note> fulnes of times: which ſheweth that God calleth and gathereth his elect, in many times, as before the law and vnder the law, and in the time of the Goſpell, wherein the whole world ſhalbe gathered And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is called by excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie the fulnes of times: Gal. 4.4. and when all ſhall be gathered, then the times ſhall be full, Rom. 11.25.26.
<note n="c" place="margin">There is but one Chriſt to ſaue all of all times and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by a diſtribution of the things to bee gathered, which are the elect: ſome in
<note n="d" place="margin">If out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, then there is no Limbus patrum, nor Purgatorie.</note> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſome ſtill founde on the earth, till the whole ſumme be called and gathered. Now
<note n="e" place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church is the companie of beleeuers in Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenand ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th.</note> all theſe ſome at one time and ſome at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being gathered, ſhall bee vnited vnto Chriſt, and then being perfect, they ſhall all be partakers of his glorie, and he ſhall giue vp his kingdome to his father. 2. Theſſ. 2.14. 1. Cor. 15.24.</p>
                     <p>Now here the maſter may learne to ſet all theſe cauſes in their right order of place, out of Rom. 8.30. <hi>Whom he predeſtinated, them alſo he called: and whom he called, them alſo he iuſtified: and whom he iuſtified, them alſo he glorified.</hi> Where vnder predeſtinated be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>his purpoſe, the good pleaſure of his will &amp; election before the foundation of the world.</hi> All the reſt is the performance of that prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination: As firſt the calling, by which is not meant the outward calling onely: but alſo the inward calling, which Chriſt ſheweth in this
<pb facs="tcp:26366:51"/>poſie:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.14</note> 
                        <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> For there is a generall calling by preaching to many, and an effectuall calling (accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preaching) by the ſpirit, in a few. Vnder this calling are contained, the ſending of Chriſt, the preaching of Chriſts Goſpel, the worke of the ſpirit, making vs to beleeue in him ſent and preached, the new birth and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>newing of the holy Ghoſt: For none are truly called, but they in whom all theſe meet. The ſecond worke of performance, is in this word <hi>inſtified:</hi> vnder which is contained our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, forginenes of ſinnes, and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of righteouſnes, which is the accepting of vs in Chriſt; the peace with God, adoption, the companion of iuſtification which is ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and his daughters ioy in the holie Ghoſt, ſtanding in grace, &amp;c. Laſtly, is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, by which is meant the finall gathering into one of all the elect vnto ſaluation, with Chriſt; when it ſhall be no ſmall part of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, to bee holie and without blame before God: (hauing no neede of earthly garments to couer our ſhame) and to praiſe God for the glory of his grace, raigning with him in fulnes of ioy for euer &amp; euer. 1. Theſſ. 3 13 Reuel. 22.1.2.3.4.7. and 22.1.2 &amp;c. and 20.6. <hi>Euen ſo Lord Ieſus come quickly. Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:26366:52"/>
               <head>The ſecond booke, containing the laſt order of inſtruction.</head>
               <p>COncerning this laſt and largeſt Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,
<note place="margin">An obſernati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the houſholder.</note> I am to admoniſh the maſter of the familie: Firſt, that I ſet downe in ſeuerall places and chapters, ſeuerall and particular places of Scripture, for the teaching of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of doctrine. The text is alway ſet before the doctrine not in the words, as in the former Catechiſmes, but onely the name of the booke, chapter, verſe, or verſes, where the words are written: which he is to peruſe and to compare with the parts of doctrine which I ſet downe; and then to reade it to his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and out of it being read, to ſhew them ſo much as I ſet downe out of it. Secondly, hee ſhall finde in ſome poynts, that they are not ſo direct, or expreſſed in the text, but are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or conſequence. Such as Chriſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.31</note> vſed, to prooue the reſurrection, if God call himſelfe the God of Abraham, &amp;c. and that he bee God of the liuing and not of the dead: then verily there is a reſurrection appoynted for the dead. Againe, wee finde that God hath
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.11</note> elected ſome vnto ſaluation before the foundation of the world, and that he doth thorowly bring to paſſe whatſoeuer he hath purpoſed. And againe we finde that
<pb facs="tcp:26366:52"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.23, 24, 25. 26.</note> ſome ſhall not bee ſaued: then it followeth, that God neuer purpoſed their ſaluation, and by conſequent he purpoſed the contrarie: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee will make God, as a
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28.</note> fooliſh buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that doth not forecaſt what hee will doe with euery part of that hee buildeth: or els i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine ſome
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.15.16.</note> other power to take order in his ouerſlippes, or els
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.12, 13, 14, 15.</note> giue him ſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers or helpers; which is as the fooliſh hath ſayd in his heart, Pſal. 14.1. Now becauſe he ſhould not ſtumble at a thing that ſeemes ſo bare, I will adde in euery ſuch place, ſome one or two plaine places of holy ſcripture, to proue the matter of ſuch a collection agreeing to faith: and theſe ſhall be alwayes in the end, or behind euery ſuch poynt. Alſo ſome one poynt by reaſon of the order of his place, may not bee contained in the text by any collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſome may be directly in the text, but not ſo cleere and plaine. Here I will alſo helpe the maſter with ſome other place direct and plaine, and by ſome one word guide him to diſcerne when any thing is not in the text. Laſtly, in teaching this Catechiſme, hee may ſometimes giue them ſome one chapter: ſometimes two for their eaſines; ſometimes but a part of one, for length or hardnes; and in all things to vſe good diſcretion. Al which rules being obſerued, hee ſhall finde I hope good vſe of this Catechiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="catechism">
               <pb facs="tcp:26366:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The laſt Catechiſme, containing</hi> the ſumme of the doctrine of Chriſt: by many places of Scripture.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 1. <hi>Of the doctrine of Chriſt. What.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Titus. 1.1.2. The doctrine of Chriſt is the knowledge of the trueth, according to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: vnder the hope of eternall life, teaching the nature and actions of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 2. <hi>Of the nature of God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Ioh. 4.24. Exod. 3.14. Reuel. 1.8. God is a ſpirit, being of himſelfe, for euer.</p>
                  <p>Ioh. 15.26. There are three perſons in the Godhead, equall in ſubſtance. The Father of whom are the reſt, in theſe words, <hi>ſent from the father.</hi> The Sonne begotten of the Father from euerlaſting. Ioh. 1.18. and 17.5. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt proceedeth from them both, in theſe words, <hi>I will ſend, and proceedeth from the father.</hi> 2. The Father worketh of himſelfe by the Sonne, and thorow the holy Ghoſt: the Sonne worketh from the Father thorow the holy Ghoſt: the holy Ghoſt worketh from the Father and the Sonne. Tit. 3.4.5.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26366:53"/>
                  <head>CAP. 3. <hi>Of the actions of God. Gods decree.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Eph. 1.11. Here the actions of God are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: which are of two ſorts. 1. The decree, which is, that he foreappoynted all things, in theſe words; <hi>purpoſe and counſell of his will, after which he worketh all things.</hi> 2. The exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the decree, which is, that he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all things according to his purpoſe, in theſe words, <hi>worketh all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here in regard of man this decree is called predeſtination, which is the foreordaining of ſome men to ſaluation, <hi>expreſſely:</hi> and ſome to damnation, <hi>by conſequent.</hi> Iud verſ. 4. Pro. 16.4. 1. Pet. 2.8. The performance of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, is by election in Chriſt, <hi>expreſsely,</hi> &amp; by reprobation from Chriſt, <hi>by conſequent; ſuch as refuſe Chriſt.</hi> Ioh. 8.42.43.47.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 4. <hi>Of the execution of Gods decree.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Pſalm. 33.6.7.8.9.10.11. The execution of Gods decree is, that he performeth his eternal purpoſe, by creating all things, verſ. 6.7.8. By gouerning all things in their times &amp; ſeaſons. verſ. 10.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 5. <hi>Of the creation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Gen. chap. 1. and chap. 2. Theſe two chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters teach vs. 1. God made all things by his
<pb facs="tcp:26366:54"/>word of nothing. 2. In ſixe daies. 3. Man in the ſixt day. 4. God made man and woman, that is, male and female in one day, cap. 1.26.27. 5. God made man of the duſt of the earth, touching his body, and breathed in him his ſoule: ſo he had both body &amp; ſoule. cap. 2.7 6. The woman was made of the man: God caſt him in a deepe ſleepe, took out one of his ribbes and cloſed vp the fleſh, and of the ribbe made the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the mans name was Adam, the womans, Eue: chap. 2.21.22. chap. 3.20. 7. The excellencie of man aboue other earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creatures, is in two thinges. 1. They were created after the image of God, which ſhineth principally in the ſoule, chap. 1.27. which is in knowledge, Coloſſ. 3.10. and practiſe of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; righteouſnes, Eph. 4.24. 2. They were created in moſt perfect happines, where vnto the image of God theſe things were ioyned; they had authoritie and Lordſhip ouer the creatures, chap. 1.28. they were ſo beautifull, that being naked they were not aſhamed. cap. 2.25.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 6. <hi>Gouernment before the fall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Gen. cap. 2. God placed man in a moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant place of the world, called the garden of Eden. verſ. 15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He gaue him commandement to keepe and to dreſſe the garden. verſ. 15.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb facs="tcp:26366:54"/>
3. He gaue him the tree of life in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the garden, as a Sacrament, that if hee continued in well doing, he ſhould liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. verſ. 9. cap. 3.22.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He gaue him this order: he might take of all the trees in the garden, except the tree of knowledge of good and euill, and in that day he ſhould eate thereof he ſhould dye the death. verſ. 16.17.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Hee inſtituted marriage, to bee of one man and one woman: that they two ſhould be one fleſh. verſ. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 7. <hi>The fall of man.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Gen. 3. In this chapter, the ſtorie of the fall of man is ſet forth, in theſe poynts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The diuell abuſing the tongue of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, entiſed the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eue, and ſhe did eate of the forbidden fruite, and ſhe gaue to her husband Adam, &amp; he did eate: and ſo the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God was broken. ver. 1.2.3. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By this diſobedience, Adam and Eue, and all mankind were dead in finne, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der damnation of bodie and ſoule, that is, hee loſt his excellencie, and became aſhamed of himſelfe, verſ. 7.8.9.10. expounded Eph. 2.1.2.3. Rom. 5.12.13.14.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To make man to ſee his owne miſerie: God curſed the earth for his ſake, that it ſhuld bring forth briers, thiſtles and thornes; made
<pb facs="tcp:26366:55"/>the man to get his liuing with toile and paine, till hee dyed: the woman with ſorrowe and griefe to bring forth and bring vp her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and baniſhed them both out of the garden of Eden, verſ. 16.17. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 8. <hi>Gouernment after the fall: The restoring of man: The two couenants.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Iere. 31.31.32.33.34. This place teacheth: 1. For the reſtoring of man, from the death of ſinne and damnation: God made two coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants: the couenant of workes, and the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of mercie. 2. The couenant of works is, that God will be our God, if wee keepe all his commaundements, verſ. 31.32. 3. The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of mercie is, God will bee our God, by forgiuenes of ſinnes thorow Chriſt, and write his lawes in our hearts, verſ. 33.34. Heb. 10.12.13.15.16. 4. We are not ſaued by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of workes, that is, by keeping of Gods commandements: for no man can do them, verſ. 32. But wee are ſaued by the couenant of mercie, that is, by beleefe in Ieſus Chriſt, by whom our ſins are forgiuen, verſ. 33.34. Rom. 8.3. Eph. 2.8.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 9. <hi>Of the first couenant, which is of workes, and the true force and perpetuall vſe of the law.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Rom. 3.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. <hi>The lawe</hi> bewrayeth ſinfulnes; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
<pb facs="tcp:26366:55"/>vs guiltie, maketh vs vnable to open our mouthes, to claime any things at Gods hand, for our owne righteouſnes or well doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: that we might run vnto Chriſt in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of mercie, to be iuſtified, and ſaued by beleefe in him, Gal. 3.21.22.</p>
                  <p>Epheſ. 2.8, 9, 10. Although we cannot bee ſaued or iuſtified by our workes or well-doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: yet God hath ordayned, the good workes commanded in his lawe, for thoſe, who ſhall be ſaued by the couenant of mercie, to walke in: as a perpetuall rule of right liuing to all beleeuers, 1. Theſſ. 4.2.3.4. with 1. Ioh. 3.6, 7, 8</p>
                  <p>Here the ten Commaundements are to be expounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 10. <hi>Of the couenant of mercie, and the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator thereof.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>2. Cor. 5.19. This teacheth the order of the couenant of mercie: namely thus. God calleth vs by his Goſpell vnto his mercie thorow Chriſt, and offereth to reconcile vs vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, thorow him, by forgiuenes of ſinnes: and we are in couenant with him, when he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs faith in Chriſts blood, Rom. 3.25. Gal. 4.4.5. This place ſheweth the mediator Chriſt; by his perſon, and office. His perſon: that he is the ſonne of God, made man: that is to ſay: perfect GOD and perfect man, in one
<pb facs="tcp:26366:56"/>perſon: man, to be like his bretheren, as Heb. 2.17. God, to be holy, harmeles, &amp;c. as Heb. 7.26. His office, to be the mediator of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of mercie, in that by his death, he redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs from vnder the lawe, to bee made the children of God.</p>
                  <p>Pſal. 110.1, 2, 3, 4. This text ſheweth the parts of Chriſts office of mediatorſhip, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that hee ſhould bee King, verſe 1.2.3. and Prieſt. verſe 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 11. <hi>Of the Prieſthoode of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1. Pet. 3.18.19. This declareth that Chriſts Prieſthoode is fulfilled in two points: 1. in his perfect obedience, as a iuſt and holy man vnto death, and all other prieſtly actions thereunto adioyned, verſe 18. Secondly, in his propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call function, verſe 19.</p>
                  <p>Rom. 8.33.34. This declareth the prieſtlie actions of Chriſt, to be of two ſortes: 1. the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his death, and his reſurrection, to put away our ſinnes, and to make vs righteous, Rom. 4.25. 2. ſitting at the right hand of God to make interceſſion for vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 12. <hi>Of the Kingdome of Chriſt, and namely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and vntill the laſt iudgement.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Epheſ. 4.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. Here is the kingly office of Chriſt deſcribed. 1. Hee is
<pb facs="tcp:26366:56"/>head of his church, who nouriſheth it, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth it in all things, verſe. 16.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This furniture is in the applying of the workes of his prieſthood, both before, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the laſt iudgement, and at the iudgement, verſe 11.12.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Before the iudgement, in two thinges: firſt, the outward pollicie and adminiſtration of his Church, verſ. 11.12. Secondly, the inward worke of his ſpirite, verſe. 11.16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The outward pollicie is adminiſtred, by officers; who are men furniſhed with giftes, to worke in the building of the Church, verſe 11.12. and theſe are of two ſortes: firſt, ſuch as teach knowledge, vnto which are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ioyned the adminiſtration of publike prayers and Sacraments, as Act. 6.4. Matth. 28.19. And theſe I finde to be either extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as Apoſtles, the founders of the church, Ephe. 2.20. and their aſſiſtants, prophets and Euangeliſts, Coloſ. 1.1.2. Tim. 4.5. or elſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as paſtors to teach by exhortation, and teachers, to vtter doctrine, Rom. 12.2.8. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, ſuch as are for practiſe of life, namely, elders to bee gouernours, 1. Cor. 12.28. and Deacons to looke to the poore, Act. 6.1, 2, 3. and for this cauſe he hath ordained the elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Matth. 18.17. 1. Tim. 4.14.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The inward worke of his ſpirit, is faith vnfayned, and knowledge, verſe 13. and the fruites of faith, which bee our growing into
<pb facs="tcp:26366:57"/>Chriſt; increaſing by his grace; loue to edifie each other, verſ. 15.16.</p>
                  <p>Rom. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Here we be taught fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruites of faith, wrought by the ſpirit: firſt, that wee bee iuſtified, to haue peace towards God, ver. 1. Secondly, adopted, to haue acceſſe to God, ver. 2. ſo opened, Rom. 8.14. &amp; of this commeth ioy vnſpeakeable, verſ. 2. with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, verſ. 3. and hope by the feeling of Gods loue, to make vs bold, verſe 4, 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 13. <hi>Of the ſeales of the couenant or Sacraments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Epheſ. 5.25, 26, 27. &amp; 1. Cor. 10.17. Theſe two places teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A ſacrament is a ſigne to repreſent, and a ſeale to applie vnto all beleeuers, the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of mercy: out of both, and is expounded, Rom. 4.11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There be two, Baptiſme and the Lords ſupper.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Baptiſme is a ſigne and ſeale of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the couenant, by the new birth and renewing of the holy ghoſt, this is in the firſt place, to which agreeth, Tit. 3.5.</p>
                  <p>The Lordes ſupper, is a ſigne and ſeale for the continuall confirming of vs in the ſame couenant, this is in the latter place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. 14. <hi>Of the last iudgement.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Matth. 25.31, 32. &amp;c. This ſhadoweth out
<pb facs="tcp:26366:57"/>the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of the adminiſtration of Chriſts kingdom, which is the laſt iudgement. Where we may learne two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The manner of Chriſtes comming vnto iudgement, namely in glory with all his holy Angels, verſ. 31.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The iudgement it ſelfe which is in two points: 1. The wonderfull meeting; firſt of the iudge Chriſt ſitting in the throne of his glory, verſ. 31. Then of the perſons to be iudged; <hi>All nations,</hi> verſ. 32. That is, all the dead raiſed in their bodies, and all the liuing chaunged, 1. Corm. 15.52. 2. In the Sentence Iudiciall, which is generall or common, that euerly one ſhall bee rewarded according to his workes, verſ. 35.42. with 2. Cor 5.10. and alſo ſpeciall or peculiar, for ſome are pronounced, Bleſſed, to inherite euerlaſting life; ver. 34.46. &amp; ſome curſed, to goe into eternal paine, verſ. 41.46,</p>
                  <p>1 Cor. 15.24.25.26.27.28. This text tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, 1. Thereſhall be an end when all rule, authoritie, and power is put downe, verſ. 24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt kingdome laſteth, till all enemies to him and his Church be deſtroyed, ver. 25.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The laſt enemie is death, which ſhall be ſwallowed vp of life, verſ. 26.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. At the end he ſhall giue vp his kingdom to God his father, and ſo (touching his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) he ſhall bee ſubiect himſelfe, that God may be all in all, verſ. 24.27.28.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="interpretation">
               <pb facs="tcp:26366:58"/>
               <head>A ſhort and plaine opening of the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</head>
               <p>THe tenne Commandements teach and command all dueties belonging to God and man, in two tables. The firſt table is of our duetie to God, in foure precepts, ſhewing what we muſt do to his perſon, and in his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt precept teacheth, that we owe vnto the perſon of God, to ſet him onely vp as the true God, firſt in our hearts, by true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his diuine nature, attributes, Trinitie, Gal. 4.8. and by a ſure confidence in him, to hope, loue, delight, reuerence and feare him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue things, Phil. 3.19. Eph. 5.5. and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by our outward profeſſion, as Ion. 1.9. and in all our workes. Pro. 3.6. His outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is in two things: 1. The meanes. 2. The right applying of the meanes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d precept teacheth the meanes, which being negatiue and naming but one thing of mans deuiſe, forbiddeth all mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, in the outward worſhip of God: &amp; commandeth onely that which God preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, which is either ordinary meanes: as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine adoration, Pſal. 95.6. The vſe of his name either ſimply, Pſal. 68.4. or in an oth, Exod. 22 11. meditation on his creatures, Pſalm. 145.1.
<pb facs="tcp:26366:58"/>praier &amp; thankſgiuing, Pſal. 50.15. the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Mat. 28.19. and his order in his church, Coloſſ. 2.5. or extraordinary, as faſting, Ioel. 2. feaſting, Eſter 9. vowing, Gen. 28.20. and in a lot, Prouer. 16.33.</p>
               <p>The right applying of the meanes of Gods worſhip, is either in the right vſe euery day, or els in the vſe of one day in ſeuen.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third precept, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth vs euery day to vſe reuerently the outward meanes of Gods worſhip, putting a part which is his name, for the whole being of the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kind, and by forbidding the euill commanding the good, which is to bee obſerued before and in the action, and after the action with profite. Leuit. 24.11. 1. Cor. 11.28.34. Ezech. 33.30.31.32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth precept teacheth the vſe of one day in ſeuen, to bee put apart from all our owne workes, to be dedicated to the worſhip of God. In the congregation by the worke of the miniſtrie, and at home in applying the ſame to the familie. Act. 20.7. Deut. 6.6.</p>
               <p>The ſecond table is of our dutie to man, in ſixe precepts, which either regard the outward action with conſent of will in 5. or els of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire onely in the laſt.</p>
               <p>The 5. are either ſpeciall dueties, or els ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fift precept teacheth ſpeciall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;
<pb facs="tcp:26366:59"/>by a part for the whole, and by propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commanding all duties of ſuperiours to inferiours and contrary, and of equals, where this any ſpeciall bond or reſpect, requiring a ſpeciall dutie. 2. Sam. 15. 1. Pet. 3.1.7.8. <hi>Loue as brethren.</hi> Generall duties belong either to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s perſon, or the things pertaining to him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixt precept teacheth duties to our neighbours perſon: commanding by a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of euill, to procure the ſafetie of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſon. Gen. 4.8. Rom. 16.4.</p>
               <p>The things belonging to his perſon, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in him, or without him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſeuenth precept, teacheth our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the things in our neighbour, as his body, 1. Cor. 6.18. by a negatiue of ill commaunds the pure and vndefiled vſing of our neighbors bodie. 2. Sam. 11.2.3.4. Gen. 39.8.9. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a man, are his goods and name.</p>
               <p n="8">8 The eight precept teacheth by a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, that wee ought to preſerue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours goods. Exod. 23.4.5.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The ninth precept teacheth by a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to tender our neighbours good name. Gen. 39.17. Pſal. 15.3.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The tenth precept teacheth, that wee ought to doe al the former ſpeciall and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dueties, with all our thoughts and deſires. 1. King. 21.12. Iam. 4.1. 1. Theſſ. 5.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="interpretation">
               <pb facs="tcp:26366:59"/>
               <head>A briefe and eaſie opening of the ſenſe of the Lords prayer, which pertaineth to the ſecond Commandement, and is to be learned after the tenne Commandements.</head>
               <p>THe Lords Prayer containeth ſixe petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, teaching vs to aske three requeſts pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Gods glorie: and three for our owne neceſſities.</p>
               <p>Concerning Gods glorie wee aske two things: that God be honored; &amp; the meanes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teacheth vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay that God may be honored in all things, Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 19.1. 1. Cor. 10.31.</p>
               <p>The meanes of Gods honour are in regard of his kingdome and will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond petition teacheth vs to pray for the aduancement of Gods kingly regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in all things, and ſpecially in his Church. Pſal. 93.1.2.3. and Pſal. 145.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third petition teacheth vs to pray for the aduancement of Gods royall will in his decree in all thinges, and his word in his Church. Pſal. 147.15.19.</p>
               <p>Concerning our ſelues, we aske things for the bodie and for the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth petition vnder the name bread, teacheth vs to aske whatſoeuer is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for this bodily life, as health, wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:26366:60"/>libertie, &amp;c. Eſay. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For the ſoule wee neede forgiuenes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>innes, and protection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sathan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 5. The fifth petition te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>earne of them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the letter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>innes then in eight dayes they haue all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ings but it muſt bee in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to know them whereſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be, in the booke, which therall our ghoſtly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a quarter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 26.41. Eph. 6.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The concluſion of the laſt order.</head>
               <p>AFter you haue paſſed thorow all theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſhiſmes, then is to be continued the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cripture in order: begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the firſt chapter of Geneſis and of Matthew: one chapter euery day of the olde Teſtament, and another of the new. In rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whereof marke two things. Firſt, what words are for the confirmation of any poynt of doctrine before learned. And ſecondly, if any thing bee hard to vnderſtand, diſpute not about it, but aske your paſtors helpe, or els ſome other godly miniſter of graue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and grounded knowledge: ſo ſhall you increaſe with great eaſe and ioy, and auoyde the
<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note> rocke, of peruerting the Scriptures, to your owne deſtruction. And as leiſure will ſerue, direct them to reade ſome other Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes and godly bookes. But aboue all
<pb facs="tcp:26366:60"/>things you muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> familie to goe to the publike preaching: for that hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> promiſe and bleſſing. And as oft as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euery daye till three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>meth into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> familie, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thorow; and laſt of al the is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſixe, or eyght lines at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea keepe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Now laſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> queſt to all gouernours of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> holders of all ſorts, poore and rich, that they would cauſe al their houſhold, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, women &amp; children, to be able to reade the Engliſh tung. For this is a worthie meanes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much good in this ſo waightie a cauſe, &amp; G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hath giuen a marueilous bleſſing of printing to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Goſpell: and wee are very fooliſh, if wee let ſlip any bleſſing or comfort, which is giuen vs of our louing and gracious father. Firſt therfore ſuch as be able I would entreat, that they would alſo helpe their ſeruants in this knowledge, and rich men ſhall make it a laudable and holy vſurie,
<note place="margin">An holy vſury.</note> to lay out ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth part of their ſuperfluities towardes the helping of poore ſeruants, and poore mens children to learne to reade, and God will pay them againe a double and treble
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro</hi> 28.27. An order for poore men &amp; ſeruants to learne to reade without loſſe of time, paine or coſt.</note> intereſt. But to ſuch as haue no other helpe or meanes, I thought good to teach an order, how they might learne with eaſe, becauſe I would not willingly leaue out any thing that might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this holy purpoſe. If they can finde ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26366:61"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be, in the booke. which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall eaſily doe in a quarter of an houre, &amp; I would not haue them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any more. Then after they know the letters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t them beſtow the like time, in like order to learne three ſeuerall wordes, to ſpell th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſtinctly, to reade them, and to poynt to euery ſillable, and to know them in any other place, being ſhewed by the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, now one and then another, and this to continue at the leaſt three weekes, or a moneth: and herein not to couet any more but three ſeuerall and new words at one time, and that in this manner: if his firſt leſſon be, <hi>In the name,</hi> and the next words be <hi>of the father,</hi> he muſt count the word, <hi>the,</hi> to be learned in his firſt leſſon, therefore the ſecond leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be, <hi>of father and:</hi> &amp; where the next words are, <hi>of the holy Ghost, Amen,</hi> he muſt account, he hath learned the two firſt words, <hi>of the,</hi> in his former leſſons, therefore his third leſſon muſt be, <hi>holy Ghost, Amen.</hi> ſo keeping in minde what he hath learned, and learning new, hee ſhould quickely learne to reade. Now after three weekes or a moneth, let him learne, in
<pb facs="tcp:26366:61"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and to keepe the points, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and by this time he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> teacher, onely let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> make himſelfe perfect, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when he meeteth with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of himſelfe by ſpelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and aske ſome one th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cher. And whoſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ently follow, and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelfe to this order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> time attaine to reade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> nes, or any toyle to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any great coſt. Then hath he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iewell, which once in his life may bee move comfort to him, then all hee hath, or all hee trauaileth for beſide. And ſo I commend you to the Lorde our God, whome I beſeech to make this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour profitable and acceptable to his church for Ieſus Chriſts ſake: and that we may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled with knowledge of his will, in all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding; that we may walke worthie of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all things, and increaſing in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. To whom bee all honor, praiſe and glorie for euer and euer, Amen,</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
